<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To his sacred maiestie, the lords spiritual, and temporal, and the House of Commons in this present Parliament assembled</title>
            <author>Crokey, Benjamin.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 137 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19613</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6045</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114520</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849745</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849745</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14912</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19613)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14912)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1347:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To his sacred maiestie, the lords spiritual, and temporal, and the House of Commons in this present Parliament assembled</title>
                  <author>Crokey, Benjamin.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>B. Alsop],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed the 1 of Iune 1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A relation of Benjamin Crokey's controversy with John Smyth concerning the Free Grammar School, Wotton-under-Edge.</note>
                  <note>At least the Bodleian Library copy has a cancel slip pasted above the first line on A2 recto, a folding flap with added text attached at the bottom of H2 verso, and many manuscript corrections.  Four hundred copies were printed; ordered burned by the Star Chamber, and Crokey and Thomas Wright, a Bristol bookseller, were fined; see S.R. Gardiner, ed., "Reports of Cases in the Courts of Star Chamber", Camden Society, 1886, pp. 37-40--STC.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Smyth, John, 1567-1640.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14912:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TO HIS SACRED MAIESTIE, THE LORDS SPIRITVAL, AND TEMPORAL, AND the Houſe of COMMONS in this preſent Parliament Aſſembled.</p>
            <p>Printed the 1. of <hi>Iune.</hi> 1625.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:14912:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Crokey</hi> being ſorie if hee ſhall offend by the tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe hereof, a more briefe then which, he knew not how to compoſe, conſidering the ſo long, ſo many and vexatious Suites wrongfully proſecuted againſt him; And in that <hi>Crokey</hi> hath in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces referred one place to another, according to the Sections and proofes, he hath done it the better to explaine and giue light to euery particular, which otherwiſe might have reſted doubtful and obſcure to the Reader.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:14912:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> True Relation of the paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in diuers Suites twelue yeares together,<note place="margin">Certificate from the Citie of <hi>Briſtol</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Seale, of <hi>Crokeyes</hi> good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, credit and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, before his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining in eſtate, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by the ſaid Suites.</note> proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Beniamin Crokey</hi> of Briſtol Merchant, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially vpon the Statute of Charitable vſes, made <hi>Anno</hi> 43. <hi>R. Regine Elizab.</hi> for and on the behalfe of a free Grammer Schoole at Wooton-vnderedge in the Countie of Gloceſter, founded by KATHERINE Lady <hi>Berkley</hi> an. 8. <hi>Richardi</hi> 2. againſt one <hi>Iohn Smith</hi> of Northnibley in the ſaid Countie Gent: who hath put in execution many ſoule and impious practices, whereby he hath moſt manifeſtly abuſed and deluded his late Majeſtie of happie memory, the Lord Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of Canterburie, the Lord Chancellor, the L.<note place="margin">Certificat of <hi>Smiths</hi> powerfulneſſe, cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and contentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and of <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keyes</hi> intollerable charges for preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that Schoole: from the Maior and Burgeſſes of <hi>Wooton,</hi> and foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene Preachers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident neere thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</note> the L. Keeper, and diuers Reuerend Biſhops, the moſt of his Majeſties Courts at Weſtminſter, &amp; Iudges thereof, and hath committed many groſſe contempts againſt the ſame Courts, &amp; all to ſupplant the foundation of that Schoole, and to get the poſſeſſion and inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance thereof, and of the Lands thereto belonging to himſelfe; the ſame being of the value of 300. pounds <hi>per annum</hi> at this day, and for which <hi>Crokey</hi> hath now a Bill depending in Parliament againſt <hi>Smith,</hi> for no other courſe of Iuſtice (by all likelihood) will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile againſt him; as that which followeth in this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation will manifeſt.</p>
            <p>May it therefore pleaſe your Majeſtie, and this Honourable Aſſembly, for the honour of GOD, and maintenance of Iuſtice, to vouchſafe the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of <hi>Crokeyes</hi> Bill againſt the ſaid <hi>Smith</hi> to bee read; and the rather, for that the Parliament foure yeares ſince was poſſeſſed with this cauſe, and
<pb facs="tcp:14912:3"/> gaue order therein, which by reaſon of the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vppe of that Parliament, <hi>Smith</hi> defeated, and went on, and renewed his former practices; And that (for your better information) it would pleaſe you to take notice of the particulars following which <hi>Crokey</hi> will proue, and in faile thereof will vndergoe what puniſhment ſoeuer this High Court ſhall inflict: all or the moſt of his proofes being noted in the Margent to the ſaid particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars in this inſuing Relation? And in this ſuite <hi>Crokey</hi> is the more earneſt, for that hee is aſſured of great oppoſition to keepe this Cauſe from the hearing of your Majeſtie, and this Honourable Aſſembly.</p>
            <div type="summary_and_brief">
               <head>1 A Summarie and Briefe of the vndue pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices by <hi>Smith</hi> before ſpoken of, for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planting the foundation of that Schole, and getting the poſſeſſions and inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance thereof to himſelfe, diſcouered and oppoſed by <hi>Crokey,</hi> mentioning eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Section where the matters are at large related, but firſt, how <hi>Smith</hi> entred and began to worke.</head>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1</hi> One <hi>Grace Drew,</hi> the Relict of one <hi>Iohn Drew,</hi> being by force of a Leaſe from the Schoole poſſeſſed of a Farme, parcell of the Poſſeſsions of that Schoole, called <hi>Warrens</hi> Court; and ſhee being very aged, decrepit, ſicke in her bed, and likely to dye; and <hi>Smith</hi> beeing a very young man, and then of little or no value or eſtate, marryed the ſaid <hi>Grace</hi> in her bed, two women holding her vp during the Ceremony, &amp; thereby <hi>Smith</hi> poſſeſſed
<pb facs="tcp:14912:3"/> himſelfe of that Farme, &amp; in this manner <hi>Smith</hi> began.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2</hi> Then <hi>Smith</hi> got the originall Leaſe of that Farme not appartaining to him, out of Chancery by cunning, and vntrue ſuggeſtions, where it was to haue been kept vntill the expiration. <hi>Sect. 8.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3 Smith</hi> bought two fraudulent Titles of the Schoole and lands from two of the <hi>Duports.</hi> And by that meanes entred vpon the Schoole and reſidue of the Schoole lands. <hi>Sect. 9.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4</hi> Then <hi>Smith</hi> placed one <hi>Cowper</hi> Schoolemaſter, and bought another fraudulent tytle of the Schoole and Lands from that <hi>Cowper,</hi> and from one <hi>Browning,</hi> and from one <hi>Bolton,</hi> the Daughter of which <hi>Browning Smith</hi> had marryed. <hi>Sect. 10.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5 Smith</hi> then let Leaſes of the Schoole Lands, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected a Court Baron, and the ſame kept diuers times in his owne name, as Lord and owner of all the Schoole Lands. <hi>Sect. 11.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6 Crokey</hi> hauing an intereſt for the reſidue of a Terme in the aforeſaid Farme called <hi>Warrens</hi> Court, and <hi>Smith</hi> keeping it from him vniuſtly, <hi>Crokey</hi> entred, and for that entrey (to out-face the world) <hi>Smith</hi> ſued <hi>Crokey</hi> in diuers Courts to weary him. <hi>Sect. 12.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7 Smith</hi> made many vntrue reports againſt <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keyes</hi> proceeding in behalfe of the Schoole, and many falſe ſuggeſtions in Courts, for maintaining his ſaid bad titles to the Schoole Lands, which plainely ſhew <hi>Smiths</hi> intent for ſupplanting the Schoole and getting the ſaid Lands. <hi>Sect. 14.15. &amp; 17.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">
                  <hi>8 Smith</hi> commenſed diuers fraudulent, and vniuſt ſuites in Star-chamber, Chancery, Exchequer, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Pleas, for maintenance and ſtrengthening his ſaid bad titles to the Schoole and Lands, wherein hee vſed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny practices, ſhifts and delayes, which alſo ſhew his ſaid intent. <hi>Sect. 17.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14912:4"/>
                  <hi>9 Smith</hi> (being diſcouered of his ſaid former bad ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles to the Schoole lands by <hi>Crokeyes</hi> oppoſition) bought another fained title of one <hi>Biſhop,</hi> of all the Schoole lands, and that managed (as the reſt) againſt <hi>Crokey</hi> which alſo ſhewed his ſaid intent. <hi>Sect. 17.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">
                  <hi>10</hi> When <hi>Crokey</hi> brought his eiectment for <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens</hi> Court, <hi>Smith</hi> obtained vpon vntrue ſuggeſtions an Iniunction in the Starchamber, which ſtayed <hi>Crokeyes</hi> proceeding at Law foure yeares, and after that Cauſe was diſmiſſed, <hi>Crokey</hi> could not get a Iury to appeare, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till <hi>48.</hi> Iurors were ſummoned. <hi>Sect. 17.19.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">
                  <hi>11 Smith</hi> interrupted <hi>Crokey</hi> three ſeuerall times in the execution of his Maieſties Commiſsion, vnder the great Seale vpon the Statute of Charitable vſes, and alſo in the execution of a ſecond Commiſsion vpon that Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, notwithſtanding his Maieſties eſpeciall directions. <hi>Sect. 20.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">
                  <hi>12 Smith</hi> practiſed with Sir <hi>Iohn Points,</hi> and one <hi>Henry Minors</hi> to finde the Schoole Lands concealed, or to draw <hi>Crokey</hi> to a Compoſition, or to intrap <hi>Crokey,</hi> that he might forbeare any further proſecution in behalfe of the Schoole. <hi>Sect. 21.22.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">
                  <hi>13 Smith</hi> made falſe ſhewes to the Countrey of a pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous intent for ſetling the Schoole, when hee knew not how otherwiſe to anſwer his former practices againſt it, and when he meant nothing leſſe. <hi>Sect. 30.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">
                  <hi>14 Smith</hi> miſuſed and euilly intreated one <hi>Prichard</hi> who ſerued as Schoolemaſter, becauſe hee inclined to <hi>Crokey</hi> in behalfe of the Schoole. <hi>Sect. 27.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">
                  <hi>15 Smith</hi> by his vndue practices hindred <hi>Crokey</hi> from obtayning a third Commiſsion vpon the Statute of Charitable vſes. <hi>Sect. 26.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">
                  <hi>16 Smith</hi> endeuoured to get a Releaſe from <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keyes</hi> Leſſee in the eiectment, at the time when the Cauſe was to be tryed, but not preuayling in that, <hi>Smith</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14912:4"/> at the tryall ſtood vpon all his bad Titles and aforeſaid practices: abuſing the Lord <hi>Hobart,</hi> and the other Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, by falſe reports and ſuggeſtions to them, and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with one <hi>Gayre</hi> to raze a Record which was done. <hi>Sect. 28.32.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="17">
                  <hi>17 Smith</hi> ſtill to delay <hi>Crokey,</hi> and to countenance his vniuſt dealings got himſelfe made a Burgeſſe in Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament of a Towne <hi>130.</hi> miles diſtant from his habitation <hi>An. 1619. Sect. 35.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="18">
                  <hi>18 Smith</hi> to weary <hi>Crokey</hi> in the proceedings for the Schoole, did ſet his agents to ſee <hi>Crokey</hi> areſted when <hi>Crokey</hi> was going on in the execution of his Maieſties Commiſsion by direction of the Parliament, and delt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derhand with <hi>Crokeyes</hi> Creditors to aſſigne <hi>Crokeyes</hi> Debts to him, or to ſome others his Agents and Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, and otherwiſe practiced whereby to keepe <hi>Crokey</hi> in Priſon, wherein hee hath preuayled againſt <hi>Crokey. Sect. 37.39.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="summary_and_brief">
               <head>2 A Summary and briefe of the ſeueral abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes committed by <hi>Smith,</hi> againſt his late Majeſtie, and againſt his Majeſties Courts, and Magiſtrates and Iudges.</head>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1</hi> By ſurmiſing falſe matter oftentimes whereby to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyd ſeueral Orders of the Starchamber for taxation of Coſts there awarded againſt him, and for increaſe of Coſts. <hi>Sect. 18.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2</hi> By detayning the ſaid ſecond Commiſſion vpon the Statute of Charitable vſes, and altering the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners names. <hi>Sect. 20.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3</hi> By deluding his Maieſtie, and the Court of Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, vnder a ſhew of a pious intent. <hi>Sect. 24.31.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4</hi> By ſurmiſing falſe matters to the Chancery, to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Crokey</hi> for obtayning a third Commiſſion. <hi>Sect. 26.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14912:5"/>
                  <hi>5</hi> By ſurmiſing falſe matter to the Iudges of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Pleas, that they might ſtay Iudgement, and Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vpon the verdict for <hi>Crokey,</hi> contrary to the Rules in Court by <hi>Smiths</hi> conſent, which falſe ſurmiſes tooke ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. <hi>Sect. 30.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6</hi> By ſurmiſing falſe matters in a Petition to his late Maieſtie, whereby <hi>Smith</hi> croſſed all former directions of his late Maieſtie, the Lord Archbiſhop of Canterbury, the Lord Chancellor, and diuers Biſhops, and other iuſt and legall proceedings in behalfe of the Schoole. <hi>Sect. 31.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7</hi> By ſurmiſing falſe matter againſt the directions of his late Maieſtie, the Archbiſhop of Canterb: the L. Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, and other Biſhops, for hindering of <hi>Crokey</hi> in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning that third Commiſsion before granted. <hi>Sect. 27.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">
                  <hi>8</hi> By making the Court of Chancery beleeue, that the Schoole Rent was brought ſo low as <hi>40.</hi> ſhillings <hi>per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> and that he had increaſed it to <hi>12.</hi> pounds <hi>per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> when as in truth the true and due Rent to the Schoole, was alwayes at the leaſt <hi>23.</hi> pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> vntill <hi>Smith</hi> began his practices to ſupplant it.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <hi>9</hi> By abuſing the Lord <hi>Hobart,</hi> and Maſter Attorney General by falſe reports and ſuggeſtions, whereby they were perſwaded of <hi>Crokeys</hi> double dealing in the cauſe of the Schoole, and thereby <hi>Smith</hi> obtained an Iniuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſtay all <hi>Crokeyes</hi> proceedings in behalfe of the Schoole. <hi>Sect. 33.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">
                  <hi>10</hi> By abuſing the Lord Keeper, and Maſter Atturney General by falſe Informations, whereby hee obtayned a Commiſsion for a ſuruey of the Schoole Lands, and the cariage thereof, which Commiſsion was directed to <hi>Smiths</hi> friends. <hi>Sect. 38.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">
                  <hi>11</hi> By abuſing the Lord Keeper, the Iudges aſsiſtants of the Chancery, and Maſter Attorney General, in draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vp and entring a Decree in Chancery, where many vntrue matters were incerted. <hi>Sect. 41. Numer. decret.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14912:5"/>
                  <hi>12.</hi> By procuring <hi>52.</hi> pounds coſts, to bee taxed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Crokey</hi> in the Starchamber vpon Bill and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>Crokeys</hi> ſuites being before ſtayed by Iniunction mentioned in the ſaid Decree, which Coſts <hi>Smith</hi> hath charged <hi>Crokey</hi> withall in the Kings Bench. <hi>Sect. 42.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="summary_and_brief">
               <head>3 A Summary and briefe of the ſeueral Contempts co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted by <hi>Smith</hi> againſt Decrees, Orders, Rules, Verdicts, and other iuſt proceedings of ſeueral Courts in the cauſe of the Schoole.</head>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi> For not bringing in the ſaid originall Leaſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to an order in Chancery, <hi>Sect. 8.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> For not ſtaying the ſaid ſuite againſt <hi>Crokey</hi> vpon his ſaid entry, according to an order in Chancery, <hi>Sect. 12.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3.</hi> For diſobeying ſeuerall orders in Starchamber for hearing, and for his boaſting againſt the ſame, <hi>Sect. 17.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4.</hi> For not attending the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mittees aſsigned by his Maieſties directions, and References for the ſchoole according to their ſeuerall warrants, <hi>Sect. 26.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5.</hi> For diſobeying the Decree by direction of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament vpon the Commiſsion of charitable vſes, and by his putting in new friuolous exceptions thereto, being before waued by conſent of <hi>Smith</hi> and his Councell, <hi>Sect. 38.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6.</hi> For his many deuiſes and ſlights by deferring the ſaid Fynall tryall, and after the tryall the Iudgement, and after the Iudgement, by not yeelding poſſeſsion ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to ſeuerall Rules in Court made by conſent of <hi>Smith</hi> and his Councell, in contempt of that Court, &amp; for procuring the Record to be razed, <hi>Sect. 28, 29, 30, 31, 32</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14912:6"/>
               <p>All which matters <hi>Crokey</hi> hopeth this high Court of Parliament will take into conſideration, and the rather when <hi>Smithes</hi> ſaid practices, abuſes, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts ſhall more fully by the particulars hereafter related appeare.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>But foraſmuch, as vpon the whole matter there may one maine queſtion ariſe, which is, that the now Lord <hi>Berkley</hi> being conceiued to be the heire of the Founder of that Schoole, and Patrone there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; why ſhould not his Lordſhip or others for him haue ſtirred in this cauſe of the Schoole, and the ſame haue defended rather then <hi>Crokey.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As to that <hi>Crokey</hi> humbly deſireth he may be called to anſwer <hi>vina voce,</hi> when he doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not but to giue good ſatisfaction therein.</p>
               </q>
               <p>There may bee alſo an Objection, which is; That <hi>Crokey</hi> hath followed the cauſe of the Schoole for ſome particular ends of his owne, and eſpecially in reſpect of his tytle to <hi>Warrens</hi> Court.</p>
               <q>As to that, <hi>Crokey</hi> doth plainely make manifeſt, that he hath not proſecuted the Cauſe of the Schoole for his owne ends, but in the behalfe of the Schoole onely and at his owne charge: for <hi>Crokey</hi> did well know his Title to <hi>Warrens</hi> Court to be good, for the Statute of the firſt of <hi>Edward</hi> the 6. maintaineth all Leaſes whatſoeuer made before the 28. day of November in the 37. of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight, as was the ſaid Leaſe vnder which <hi>Crokey</hi> claimes.</q>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:14912:6"/>
               <head>The particulars of the Relation are, as they doe appeare by the ſeuerall Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the proofes whereof are noted in the Margent.</head>
               <p n="1">1. AN Inquiſition vpon an <hi>ad quod damnum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Copy of the Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>die lune proxime ante feſtum Aſſentionum Domini, Anno</hi> 7. <hi>Regni regis Ricardi ſecundi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. King <hi>Richard</hi> the 2. granted licence of the 16. of Iune,<note place="margin">Copy of the Licence.</note> in the 7. of his reigne to <hi>Walter Burnell</hi> and <hi>William Pendock</hi> Chaplaines, for erecting of a free Grammer ſchoole in Wooton-vnderedge in the Countie of Gloceſter, and for indowment thereof, with the land and Tenements therein mentioned for maintenance and ſuſtentation of a Maſter, and two poore Schollers, and their ſucceſſors for euer.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Berkley,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Copy of the Licence.</note> Lord of <hi>Berkley</hi> gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Licence Dated 1. Iuly Anno 8. <hi>Regni regis Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cardi</hi> 2. to the ſaid <hi>Walter Burnell</hi> and <hi>William Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dock,</hi> for erecting the ſaid Schoole, and for indow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof with the Lands in the ſame Licence mentioned, for maintenance and ſuſtentation of a Maſter and two poore Schollers, and their ſucceſſors for euer.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That the 20. day of October in the ſaid eight yeare of the reigne of King <hi>Richard</hi> the 2.<note place="margin">Copy of the Grant.</note> a Grant was made by the ſaid <hi>Walter Burnell</hi> and <hi>William Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dock,</hi> at the charges and procurement of <hi>Katherine</hi> Lady <hi>Berkley,</hi> for erecting the ſaid Schoole, and for indowment thereof with the Lands and Tenements in the ſame Grant mentioned, for maintenance and ſuſtentation of a Maſter and two poore Schollers, for teaching of Schollers in the Art and rudiments of Grammer; the Patronage of which Schoole
<pb facs="tcp:14912:7"/> was intayled vpon the heires males of the ſaid <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> Lord <hi>Berkley.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">An exemplification of a Record and <hi>Smiths</hi> Decree in Chancery, <hi>Sect. 40. Numero 7.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. In this eſtate the Schoole continued for the ſpace of 200. yeares, and vntill <hi>Smith</hi> endeuoured to alter the ſame; and the Lands belonging to the Schoole are worth 300. pound<note n="a" place="margin">Certificate of the Archibiſhop of Cant: Biſhops of London and Winton to his Maieſtie.</note> 
                  <hi>per annum</hi> at this day.</p>
               <p n="6">6. That <hi>Robert Coldewell</hi> was Schoolemaſter of that Schoole, duly preſented, and was in right there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſeized of and in all the lands &amp; Tenements there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to belonging, and being ſo ſeized, by his<note n="b" place="margin">Confeſſed by <hi>Smiths</hi> ſaid Decree in Chancery, <hi>Sect. 40. Numero. 8.</hi>
                  </note> Inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture vnder the common Seale of that Schoole, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring date the 27. of May, in the 37. yeare of the reigne of King <hi>Hen.</hi> the 8. did demiſe one meſſuage with the appurtenances called Warrens Court, in North-Nibley in the ſaid County of Gloceſter, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of the ſaid Schoole lands, vnto one <hi>William Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> his Executors &amp; Aſſignes, from the feaſt of the Anunciation of the bleſſed Lady S. <hi>Mary</hi> the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin then laſt paſt, for the terme of 88. yeares, for the yearely Rent of fourtie eight ſhillings.</p>
               <p>That <hi>William Thomas</hi> by his laſt<note n="c" place="margin">Confeſſed by the ſame Decree, <hi>Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero 8.</hi>
                  </note> Will, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1556. did bequeath the ſaid Leaſe and reſidue of the Terme of 88. yeares, vnto <hi>Alice</hi> his wife and Executrix for her life, and after to <hi>Grace</hi> Daughter of the ſaid <hi>William Thomas</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice,</hi> and after to the Children of the ſaid <hi>Alice</hi> by <hi>Iohn Moore</hi> her former Husband, and to the ſurui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor of them, which children were <hi>Richard, Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam, Katherine, Elizabeth, Mary,</hi> and <hi>Ioice,</hi> and dyed. <hi>Alice</hi> proued that<note n="d" place="margin">Will vnder Seale.</note> will, and entred into Warrens Court as a Legacy, and ſo left the ſame after her death to <hi>Grace,</hi> who at the ſuite of the ſaid <hi>Richard Moore,</hi> and the reſt of his ſaid Brethren and Siſters being plaintiffes, againſt the ſaid <hi>Alice</hi> and <hi>Grace,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14912:7"/> were by an<note n="e" place="margin">2. <hi>Orders.</hi>
                  </note> order in Chancery (where that ſuite was commenced) in the 26. yeare of the reigne of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> compelled to bring the ſaid ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall Leaſe into that Court, where it was by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of <hi>Alice,</hi> and all the ſaid Legatees to<note n="f" place="margin">An Exemplifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Anſwers of <hi>Alice</hi> and <hi>Grace.</hi>
                  </note> remaine and ſafely there be kept for the vſe of them all; that they might take the benefit thereof one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, vntill the expiration thereof.</p>
               <p n="8">8. That the ſaid Leaſe was ſo kept the ſpace of 18. yeares, and vntill <hi>Smith</hi> married the ſaid <hi>Grace,</hi> which was in the 39. yeare of the reigne of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and then <hi>Smith</hi> (perceiuing that all other the ancient Leaſes of the Schoole lands were come to an end, except the Leaſe of Warrens Court) began his endeuours and practices to get all the ſaid Schoole lands, and to that purpoſe did by diuers practices and vntrue ſuggeſtions in Chancery (there being then none to oppoſe him)<note n="g" place="margin">Order.</note> obtaine the ſaid Leaſe out of Chancery vnduly, and the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned in contempt of the<note n="h" place="margin">Order.</note> Orders of that Court.</p>
               <p n="9">9. That <hi>Smith</hi> (hauing ſo gotten that Leaſe) delt and practiced with one <hi>Henry Duport,</hi> that <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port</hi> ſhould<note n="i" place="margin">Copy of <hi>Smiths</hi> Anſwer to <hi>Biſhops</hi> Bill in the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, and of the Bill.</note> pretend ſome tytle to the Patronage of that Schoole, and to the inheritance of the Lands thereto belonging; whereupon <hi>Smith</hi> and that <hi>Duport</hi> gaue forth in ſpeeches, that the ſaid <hi>Duport</hi> had good tytles thereunto, and <hi>Smith</hi> alſo practiced with <hi>Iohn Duport,</hi> and <hi>Iames Duport</hi> (who then had poſſeſſed themſelues of the ſaid Schoole and Lands as maſters and owners thereof) to ſet on foot ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tytle; and ſo <hi>Smith</hi> for ſome ſmall matter to thoſe three <hi>Duports</hi> got poſſeſſion of all the Schoole-Lands as his owne Fee-ſimple, and likewiſe the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage, and the better to colour that his practice<note n="k" place="margin">Counterpart of the Conueyance, razed in the ſumme let downe for conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> tooke conveyances from the <hi>Duports.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">
                  <pb facs="tcp:14912:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>10. That <hi>Smith</hi> Anno 6. <hi>Regni regis Iacobi</hi> vnduly placed one <hi>Edward Cowper</hi> Maſter of that Schoole, vpon whoſe induction <hi>Smith</hi> cauſed <hi>Cowper</hi> to<note n="l" place="margin">Copy of <hi>Smiths</hi> Anſwer in the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, and of the Bill.</note> conuey all the Schoole Lands in Fee to one <hi>Iohn Browning</hi> father to <hi>Smiths</hi> wife, and to one <hi>Bolton,</hi> which <hi>Browning</hi> and <hi>Bolton</hi> ſoone after conueyed the ſame and leuied a Fine to <hi>Smith</hi> and his heires for euer, and ſo <hi>Cowper</hi> continued as Schoole-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, but neuer exerciſed the place, or had any thing there to doe, but others as Deputies there were pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by <hi>Smith,</hi> and ſo <hi>Smith</hi> made <hi>Cowper</hi> but as his ſtale.</p>
               <p n="11">11. That <hi>Smith</hi> (by colour of the ſaid ſeuerall conveyances, and vpon expiration of all the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Leaſes about that time, <hi>viz.</hi> about <hi>Anno</hi> 6. <hi>Regni regis Iacobi</hi> worne out, ſauing the ſaid Leaſe of Warrens Court)<note n="m" place="margin">Copy of <hi>Smiths</hi> ſaid Anſwer in the Exchequer, and of the Bill.</note> entred<note n="n" place="margin">Smiths <hi>Patent.</hi>
                  </note> vpon 38. Tenements belonging to that Schoole, hauing poſſeſſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of Warrens Court before, and did let thoſe Tenements for long termes vpon Fines, and the Tenants tooke Bonds of <hi>Smith</hi> for the quiet enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;<note n="o" place="margin">Witneſſes.</note> and ſhortly after <hi>Smith</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Witneſſes.</note> called a Court Baron in his owne name, as Lord and owner of all the Schoole lands, and ſummoned all the Tenants of the Schoole lands as belonging to Warrens Court, and kept Courts Baron in the Schoole-houſe.</p>
               <p n="12">12. That the ſaid <hi>Ioice</hi> was laſt ſuruiuor of all the ſaid Legatees, as <hi>Smith</hi> hath<note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Smiths</hi> Decree in Chancery.</note> confeſſed, and the ſaid <hi>Ioice</hi> (ſo being lawfully intytled vnto all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine of 88. yeares in Warrens Court, which was 21. yeares then to come) did for diuers conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons duly<note n="r" place="margin">Aſſignement from <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oice</hi> to <hi>Crokey</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>ant of Attor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</note> aſſigne the ſame Leaſe to <hi>Crokey</hi> her Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew (which <hi>Crokey,</hi> was ſonne of the ſaid <hi>Kathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine</hi> one of the ſaid Legatees) and dyed inteſtate, and <hi>Crokey</hi>
                  <note n="ſ" place="margin">Letters of Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>ation.</note> adminiſtred, and this was about 12.
<pb facs="tcp:14912:8"/> yeares ſince, whereupon <hi>Crokey</hi> (being intereſſed in Warrens Court, and <hi>Smith</hi> being in poſſeſſion thereof, and the ſaid <hi>Grace</hi> his then late wife being dead, and by her death <hi>Smiths</hi> intereſt in Warrens Court ending) <hi>Crokey</hi> commenced a ſuite in Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery againſt <hi>Smith,</hi> and made his entry thereinto, and depending the ſaid ſuite in Chancery <hi>Smith</hi> (ſtill to colour his bad tytles to outface the world, and to vex <hi>Crokey</hi> with ſuites) brought an action of treſpaſſe againſt <hi>Crokey</hi> for that his entry; in which ſuite <hi>Smith</hi> proceeded to tryall without <hi>Crokeyes</hi> priuity, and ſo that Tryall paſſed by default, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>Smith</hi> recouered of <hi>Crokey</hi> 7. pounds for coſts, though <hi>Crokey</hi> at the beginning of that ſuite obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned an<note n="t" place="margin">Order.</note> order in Chancery for ſtay thereof, or to ſhew cauſe to the contrary which <hi>Smith</hi> did not, but in contempt went to tryall as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p n="13">13. By theſe ſuites with <hi>Smith</hi> for Warrens Court, <hi>Crokey</hi> tooke knowledge of the foundation and ſtate of the Schoole, and withall of <hi>Smiths</hi> ſaid practices againſt the ſame, which practices of <hi>Smith</hi> ſtirred vp <hi>Crokey</hi> more for defence of the Schoole, then for his owne tytle as may well appeare by that which followeth.</p>
               <p n="14">14. That there haue beene 33. ſeuerall<note n="u" place="margin">Seuerall Records exemplified, and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies of Record.</note> ſuites touching the ſaid Will of the ſaid <hi>William Thomas,</hi> whereupon there were Virdicts, Decrees, Non-ſuites, and Diſmiſſions: and the queſtion in all which ſuites was, whether that the remainder of yeares in Warrens Court ſhould goe and be to the Legatees, or to the Executors by the ſaid Will, in all which ſuites Iudgement was alwaies for the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatees vnder whom <hi>Crokey</hi> claymes, and <hi>Crokey</hi> hath an approued good and lawfull tytle to Warrens Court during the remainder of 88. yeares, and
<pb facs="tcp:14912:9"/> 
                  <hi>Smith</hi> hath no right thereunto, nor had ſince the death of <hi>Grace</hi> his ſaid wife; howbeit <hi>Smith</hi> by his vntrue reports ordinarie with him, and by ſome falſe colours hath ſo ſhadowed the matter, as that he hath made all men beleeue, that all the ſaid ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſuites were in affirmation of his vniuſt clayme, vnder a pretended tytle from one <hi>Sprint,</hi> coloured by a Decree in Chancery 19. May, 43. <hi>R. Regine Elizab.</hi> obteyned by <hi>Smith</hi> deceitfully, as alſo by a diſmiſſion cauſed by colour of that Decree, which Decree and diſmiſſion were againſt one <hi>Moores</hi> Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, not againſt <hi>Crokeyes;</hi> which Decree and diſmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on laſt ſpoken of, or his ſaid pretended tytle from <hi>Sprint, Smith</hi> in all his ſuites with <hi>Crokey,</hi> or in any of them could neuer make good: though <hi>Smith</hi> hath laboured therein all he might, but the ſame were alwaies held and deemed deceitfull and fraudulent.</p>
               <p n="15">15. That <hi>Crokey</hi> (for his owne right, but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in his tenderneſſe and zeale for preſeruation of the Schoole and inheritance thereof) proſecuting the before mentioned ſuite in Chancery againſt <hi>Smith, Smith</hi> (further to colour thoſe his practices before ſpoken of for maintenance of his iniurious dealing againſt the Schoole and <hi>Crokey</hi>) exhibited an<note n="u" place="margin">Exemplification of the Triall.</note> Information againſt <hi>Crokey</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Ioice Crokeyes</hi> Aunt to the court of Common pleas vpon the Statute of Maintenance and Champerty, which ſuite was commenced 20. Iuly <hi>Anno</hi> 12. <hi>Regni regis Iacobi;</hi> in which<note n="x" place="margin">Information.</note> Information, he the ſaid <hi>Smith</hi> ſet forth, that the firſt day of Ianuary in the 11. yeare of his Maieſties raigne, and by the ſpace of two yeares next before he was, and then was ſeized in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaſne as of fee of and in one capital meſſuage cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Warrens Court, and of and in 60. Acres of land, 20. acres of meddow, and 30. acres of paſture,
<pb facs="tcp:14912:9"/> and 20. Acres of Wood, ſcituate and lying in <hi>North-Nibley</hi> in the County of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> and the Rents and profits of the ſame Tenements with the appurtenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to his owne proper vſe for all the ſaid time of 2. yeares had and receiued, <hi>Smith</hi> pretending further thereby, that <hi>Ioice</hi> not hauing any right or title, and notwithſtanding pretending right and tytle to the premiſes conueyed the ſame to <hi>Crokey,</hi> and ſo both <hi>Ioice</hi> and <hi>Crokey</hi> within the Statute of Maintenance and Champerty; to which Information <hi>Ioice</hi> and <hi>Crokey</hi> pleaded, and the cauſe came to tryall at the Bar. 26. April <hi>Anno</hi> 13. <hi>Regni regis Iacobi,</hi> &amp; vpon full euidence <hi>Smith</hi> was<note n="y" place="margin">The ſame Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plification.</note> nonſuited, and yet vpon ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the ſaid ſuite in Chancery (which was but 3. dayes after the ſaid tryall) <hi>Smith</hi> by his indirect pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices procured a<note n="z" place="margin">Order.</note> diſmiſſion to the Law without any further hearing.</p>
               <p n="16">16. That vpon the ſaid Diſmiſſion in Chancery, <hi>Crokey</hi> ſealed a<note n="a" place="margin">The Leaſe for try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of the tytle.</note> Leaſe for 5. yeares to one <hi>Thomas Bodham</hi> whereon to bring an action of <hi>eiectione firme,</hi> for tryall of the tytle, and thereupon <hi>Crokey</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menced a ſuite in the Court of Common pleas a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Smith;</hi> In which ſuite the Iudges of that Court (perceiuing the many vniuſt ſuites and ſiniſter pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices raiſed and proſecuted by <hi>Smith</hi> againſt <hi>Crokey</hi> &amp; againſt the Schoole) made ſeueral<note n="b" place="margin">The Rules.</note> Rules in Court (but with the aſſent of <hi>Smith</hi> and his Councel) that if the verdict vpon that Tryall ſhould paſſe for <hi>Crokey,</hi> that then <hi>Crokey</hi> ſhould forthwith haue poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, and no writ of Error ſhould be granted, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the ſaid Leaſe for the eiectment ſhould be expired.</p>
               <p n="17">17. That <hi>Smith</hi> (to weary <hi>Crokey</hi> in that ſuite with vexations and delayes as before in the reſt he ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured) in May <hi>Anno Regni regis Iacobi</hi> 13. commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced a new ſuite in Chancery againſt <hi>Crokey</hi> for the
<pb facs="tcp:14912:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſame cauſe, which was<note n="c" place="margin">Order of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.</note> diſmiſſed in Iuly, <hi>Anno</hi> 15. <hi>Regni regis Iacobi:</hi> And alſo another ſuite by <hi>Engliſh</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Copy of <hi>Smithes</hi> Anſwer to the ſaid Bill.</note> Bill in the Exchequer Chamber <hi>Termino Paſo: An.</hi> 14. <hi>Regni regis Iacobi</hi> in the name of one <hi>Edw: Biſhop</hi> a friend of <hi>Smiths,</hi> and his chamber-fellow in the inner Temple, which ſuite though it ſeemed to bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menced againſt <hi>Smith</hi> (for therein he made himſelfe defendant and anſwered the ſaid Bill) yet that Bill was exhibited by <hi>Smith</hi> himſelfe fraudulently, &amp; the ſame Bill <hi>Smith</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">The ſaid Copy of <hi>Smiths</hi> Anſwer.</note> anſwered, and in that his Anſwer ſtood vpon all his fayned tytles, and <hi>Smith</hi> likewiſe tooke out a<note n="f" place="margin">Order.</note> Commiſſion for examination of wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>ed diuers witneſſes to proue that Bill, and ſo proued the Bill, and thereby, that all the lands belonging to the Schoole were concealed and within the Statute of 1. <hi>Edw:</hi> 6. and ſo that ſuite cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and all that ſuite was at <hi>Smiths</hi> charge, for there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he made himſelfe both plantiffe and defendant; whereupon <hi>Smith</hi> (for little or nothing) bought <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> tytle, but withall tooke letters<note n="g" place="margin">Copy of the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Patents. Copy of Certificate and Decree vpon the Commiſſion for Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable vſes: and Witneſſes.</note> Patens thereof vpon the Commiſſion of defectiue tytles to him and his heires for euer, for which he paid to his Maieſtie 5. pound, and was to pay xi. <hi>s.</hi> Rent <hi>per annum,</hi> by which tytles <hi>Smith</hi> meant to hold the Schoole lands as he holdeth other<note n="h" place="margin">Note from the Rolls.</note> land in <hi>Suſſex</hi> by thoſe tytles to this day; And further about the ſame time (ſtill to delay <hi>Crokeys</hi> ſaid ſuite vpon the Eiectment) <hi>Smith</hi> commenſed (or rather but reuiued his other foyled ſuite of Maintenance and Champerty, which before he had brought in the common pleas) a ſuite in the Starchamber againſt <hi>Crokey,</hi> and foure others, <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keyes</hi> friends for maintenance and Champerty, therein ſurmiſing forgerie, and periurie, wherein <hi>Smith</hi> alſo pretended a tytle of inheritance to Warrens Court, whereupon, and vpon other falſe ſuggeſtions, <hi>Smith</hi> obtained an<note n="i" place="margin">Order.</note> Iniunction for
<pb facs="tcp:14912:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſtay of <hi>Crokeyes</hi> ſaid tryall vpon the Eiectment, and by that meanes the ſaid Tryall was ſtayed foure yeares to <hi>Crekeyes</hi> great vexation and trouble, and to his expence of foure hundred pounds or therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts in that proceeding, <hi>Crokey</hi> being inforced to attend that Court euery Terme with councell for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluing that Iniunction, but could not, but in the end was inforced to labour for a hearing, for which he procured foure ſeuerall peremptorie<note n="k" place="margin">4. <hi>Orders.</hi>
                  </note> Orders in foure ſeuerall Termes for hearing of the ſaid Star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber cauſe ſo commenced by <hi>Smith,</hi> during which delay <hi>Smith</hi> gaue forth in<note n="l" place="margin">Affidauit.</note> ſpeeches, that he would weary <hi>Crokey</hi> by ſuites in Law, and that it was as poſſible for <hi>Crokey</hi> to remoue a Mountaine, as to preuaile againſt him the ſaid <hi>Smith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="18">18. That after foure yeares toyle and ſuite in the Starchamber, that cauſe there depending by <hi>Crokeyes</hi> great trauaile and coſt was heard, and <hi>Crokey,</hi> and the reſt of the Defendants were abſolutely<note n="m" place="margin">Order.</note> diſmiſſed with good coſts, but when the coſts ſhould haue beene taxed; <hi>Smith</hi> ſo practiced and wrought, as that <hi>Crokey</hi> could not get them to be taxed, but was inforced diuers times to moue that Court for order therein, whereupon in the time of the Lord Chancellor, the Lord <hi>Mandevile,</hi> and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Lord Keeper, <hi>Crokey</hi> obteyned diuers Orders in open Court for the Coſts<note n="n" place="margin">Seuerall Orders.</note> to be taxed, with increaſe of Coſts for <hi>Smiths</hi> delayes: which coſts were drawne vp to<note n="o" place="margin">Bills of Coſts.</note> 297. pound, and (notwithſtanding the ſaid Diſmiſſion and Orders) <hi>Crokey</hi> could not obteine Coſts to be taxed; whereupon <hi>Crokey</hi> in May 1623. Petitioned the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Lord Keeper therein, but ſo farre was his Lordſhip abuſed by the falſe ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions and practices of <hi>Smith,</hi> and ſo much incenſed againſt <hi>Crokey,</hi> that his Lordſhips Anſwere<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Crokeyes</hi> Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the Lord Keepers Anſwere thereto.</note> to that Petition was, and ſo ſubſcribed it, that <hi>Crokey</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14912:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> deſerued to haue his eares cropt off for abuſing him, in that his Lordſhip neuer refuſed to taxe Coſtes at the end of euery Terme: And yet <hi>Graſvenor Crokeyes</hi> Attourney did<note n="q" place="margin">Affidauit.</note> affirme, that hee often had preſented the Bill of Coſtes to his Lordſhip to bee taxed, and that hee was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer more wearied then with vrging his Lordſhip therein, and for that his Lordſhip had deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to doe it, hee durſt not moue the ſame againe; But ſhortly after vpon vntrue ſuggeſtions by one Maſter <hi>Trotman</hi> of <hi>Smithes</hi> Councell, and by <hi>Smithes</hi> practices together, and without the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie of <hi>Crokey,</hi> or his Councell, or Attourney <hi>Smith</hi> obtained<note n="r" place="margin">Order.</note> Order for remitting all the ſaid Coſts, which Order <hi>Crokey</hi> could not get to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſed.</p>
               <p n="19">19. That (the ſaid Starchamber cauſe being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed) <hi>Crokey</hi> laboured very earneſtly many Termes for a Tryall vpon the ſaid Leaſe of eiect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment according to the ſaid Rules in Court, and to his great trouble and charge brought vp his Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes (ſome of whom dwelling one hundred miles from <hi>London</hi>) and divers Termes fee'd his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell and<note n="ſ" place="margin">Copy of the Panell and Diſtringas.</note> 48. Iurors were ſummoned before a Iury did appeare, And ſo after foure yeares delay and more, the ſaid cauſe was tryed at the Common Pleas Barre, <hi>viz. Termino Paſe: Anno</hi> 18. <hi>Regnire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis Iacobi,</hi> And vpon the ſayd Tryall it was found for <hi>Thomas Bodham Crokeyes</hi> Leſſee in the eiectment, as is more at large related in the 28, 29. &amp; 30. . and how <hi>Crokey</hi> was delayed in the Iudgement and altogether defeated.</p>
               <p n="20">20. That depending the ſaid ſuites, and <hi>Crokey</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing fully informed himſelfe of the eſtate of the Schoole, and of <hi>Smithes</hi> practiſes for ſupplanting thereof, and getting all the ſaid Schoole lands, <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>key</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14912:11"/> (to reſtore the ſaid Schoole, and to reduce all things into their former being, according to the ſaid foundation) <hi>Anno</hi> 1617. obtained a Commiſſion to inquire of the whole matter concerning the ſaid Schoole and the lands thereto anciently belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, according to the ſaid Statute of Charitable vſes; And for execution of the ſaid Commiſſion, <hi>Crokey</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">The Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners Warrants.</note> procured a day to bee appointed, and prouided his Witneſſes and all matters incident thereto, and alſo got a<note n="u" place="margin">Witneſſes.</note> Iurie to appeare, but all was defeated by the practices and power of <hi>Smith,</hi> and a ſecond time in like manner: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Crokey</hi> peticioned to his late Maieſtie, and his Maieſtie (being gratiouſly inclined to the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of the charitable and good courſe of the Lawe and Statute in that caſe prouided) was pleaſed according to his Maieſties Commiſſion vnder the great Seale of <hi>England</hi> before granted, that the Biſhop of Gloceſter and any 4. of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners in that Commiſſion named, ſhould with conuenient ſpeed enter into the examination of this cauſe, and according to the authority giuen to them in the ſame Commiſſion finally determine and effect the ſame, ſo as there ſhould be no cauſe giuen of any further trouble to his Maieſtie, as by his Maieſties<note n="*" place="margin">Petition and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</note> direction ſignified by Sir <hi>Daniel Dun</hi> 5. September 1617. may appeare; which ſaid Commiſſion, and that his Maieſties direction notwithſtanding, by like practices of <hi>Smith</hi> was interrupted and defeated a third time, and ſo <hi>Crokey</hi> loſt that Commiſſion, and all his labour and charge, and nothing done there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. And in the yeare 1618. <hi>Crokey</hi> procured a<note n="x" place="margin">Warrant.</note> War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for a ſecond Commiſſion from the Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor for the ſame purpoſe; which<note n="y" place="margin">Commiſſion.</note> Commiſſion being ingroſſed in the Crowne office, and ready for the Seale (<hi>Crokey</hi> hauing then paid the charge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of)
<pb facs="tcp:14912:12"/> was by like practices of <hi>Smith</hi> there kept from <hi>Crokey</hi> for 2 moneths and more. And whilſt the ſaid Commiſſion was ſo ſtayed in the Crown office <hi>Smith</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">Witneſſes.</note> practiced with one <hi>Iohn Hunt</hi> to alter the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners names, contrary to the Warrant deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in by <hi>Crokey,</hi> and ſo that Commiſſion was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſed of new, and ſome of the Commiſſioners names in the Warrant were left out in the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,<note n="a" place="margin">Commiſſion vnder the great Seale.</note> and others of <hi>Smiths</hi> friends put in: howbeit <hi>Crokey</hi> took that Commiſſion as it was, and laboured for the execution thereof, and a day<note n="b" place="margin">Warrant for day of Sitting Witneſſes.</note> was appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and <hi>Crokey</hi> with Iurors and Witneſſes, and all things elſe ready on his part to haue beene done, but by the like practices of <hi>Smith</hi> there did come to the place aſſigned for execution of the ſaid Commiſſion but three<note n="c" place="margin">Certificate of the Commiſſion.</note> Commiſioners of 7. that had ſigned the Warrants, when no leſſe then foure could execute it, whereby that Commiſſion was alſo avoided, and all <hi>Crokeyes</hi> labours and charges loſt.</p>
               <p n="21">21. That in the meane time the Commiſſion was ſo kept back, <hi>Smith</hi> practiced with Sir <hi>Iohn Pointz</hi> Knight, and one <hi>Henry Minors</hi> to take a Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on forth of the Exchequer, whereby to finde the poſſeſſions of the ſaid Schoole to be<note n="d" place="margin">Witneſſes.</note> concealed as Chantry lands giuen to ſuperſtitious vſe, and within the Statute 1. <hi>Edward</hi> 6. wherein <hi>Smith</hi> ſo handled the matter, as that Sir <hi>Iohn Pointz</hi> and <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors</hi> did take ſuch a Commiſſion forth of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, and being Patentees<note n="e" place="margin">Bond from Sir <hi>Iohn Pointz</hi> and <hi>minors</hi> to <hi>Crokey.</hi>
                  </note> were alſo therein made Commiſſioners.</p>
               <p n="22">22 That the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Pointz</hi> and <hi>Minors,</hi> about Auguſt <hi>Anno</hi> 1618. went to <hi>Tidbury</hi> in the ſaid County of Gloceſter for execution of their ſaid Commiſſion, where (hauing a Iurie<note n="f" place="margin">Witneſſes.</note> of ſimple men, ſome whereof being of <hi>Smiths</hi> kindred) yet that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they would not proceed at that time,
<pb facs="tcp:14912:12"/> becauſe <hi>Crokey</hi> was there ready with all things for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Schoole and poſſeſſions thereof, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other things with a Caſe<note n="g" place="margin">Caſ</note> drawne and reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by Sir <hi>Henry Yelverton</hi> and Sir <hi>Thomas Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentry</hi> his late Maieſties Councell at Law vnder their hands, affirming that the ſaid Schoole and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions were free from ſuperſtitious vſes, and no way within the ſaid Statute of 1. <hi>Edward</hi> 6. whereupon Sir <hi>Iohn Pointz</hi> ſoone after laboured <hi>Crokey</hi> very ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly for a compoſition, which <hi>Crokey</hi> vtterly refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſoone after that Sir <hi>Iohn Pointz</hi> and <hi>Minors</hi> met againe vpon their ſaid Commiſſion at <hi>Wickware</hi> in the ſaid County of Gloceſter, <hi>viz.</hi> the 13. of<note n="h" place="margin">Witneſſes and Warrant from Sir <hi>Iohn Pointz</hi> and <hi>Minors.</hi>
                  </note> October 1618. At which time <hi>Crokey</hi> likewiſe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, but before they ſate both Sir <hi>Iohn Pointz</hi> and <hi>Minors</hi> earneſtly preſſed <hi>Crokey</hi> to a compoſition, which <hi>Crokey</hi> againe vtterly refuſed as before, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they proceeded with a like ſimple Iurie as they beſt pleaſed, notwithſtanding <hi>Crokey</hi> ſtood in<note n="i" place="margin">Witneſſes.</note> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Schoole in all he might, and ſo it was found, that the ſaid Schoole and lands thereto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing were giuen to ſuperſtitious vſes, and within the Statute of 1. <hi>Edw:</hi> 6. and yet the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Pointz</hi> and <hi>Minors</hi> laboured againe at that time with <hi>Crokey</hi> for a Compoſition, and offered their<note n="k" place="margin">Bond.</note> Bond of 2000. pound to <hi>Crokey</hi> with condition for the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of <hi>Warrens</hi> Court to <hi>Crokey</hi> and his heires in Fee farme, and to ſet him in poſſeſſion thereof; And albeit <hi>Crokey</hi> well did know that all their offers were but to intrap and to draw him from defending the Schoole, and that by <hi>Smiths</hi> plot and practice, yet <hi>Crokey</hi> alſo perceiuing that they profered him ſome aduantage whereby they might afterwards intrap themſelues, was content to take ſuch a Bond, ſo as he might haue the drawing of the Bond and Condition which they aſſented gladly vnto, and ſo <hi>Crokey</hi> did cauſe the
<pb facs="tcp:14912:13"/> Bond and Condition to be drawne, wherein he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sir <hi>Iohn Pointz</hi> and <hi>Minors</hi> to bee mentioned both Patentees and Commiſſioners, which was all that thereby <hi>Crokey</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Witneſſe Maſter <hi>Hart.</hi>
                  </note> ſought, to the end the practices by them and <hi>Smith</hi> might the better appeare; <hi>Crokey</hi> then knowing no other, or better way for diſcouery of their ſaid practices, neither did <hi>Crokey</hi> ſo much as promiſe, much leſſe aſſure to them any thing at all, but forthwith ſhewed to the Lords grace of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> the ſaid Bond, and fully acquainted his Grace therewith, and of all their other practices againſt the Schoole, as formerly he had done.</p>
               <p n="23">23. That thereupon his Grace ſent his Soliciter<note n="m" place="margin">Witneſſe. Maſter <hi>Hart.</hi>
                  </note> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Hart</hi> with <hi>Crokey</hi> to the Lord chiefe Baron of the Exchequer for trauerſing of the ſaid vndue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, &amp; reuerſing of the ſaid Inquiſition, and (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Lord cheefe Barons direction) <hi>Crokey</hi> moued that Court of Exchequer by his Councell, whereupon a day was giuen to Sir <hi>Iohn Pointz</hi> and <hi>Minors</hi> to come in for maintaining their ſaid Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which they refuſing to doe, the ſaid Inquiſition, and Commiſſion by an expreſſe<note n="n" place="margin">Order.</note> order in that Court were ſuppreſſed and made voide.</p>
               <p n="24">24. That <hi>Smith</hi> (to manifeſt his craft in dawbing) did then alſo moue the Court of Exchequer by his Councell for making voide the ſaid Inquiſition, and Commiſſion, whereupon in the ſaid<note n="o" place="margin">Order.</note> Order the name of <hi>Smithes</hi> Councell was foiſted, in ſtead of <hi>Crokeys</hi> Councell, as if <hi>Smith</hi> had beene the chiefe and onely oppoſor, and not the procurer of the ſaid laſt mentioned Commiſſion and Inquiſition, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>Smith</hi> did not onely delude the ſaid Court of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, but the Country alſo for when he perceiued that Plot with <hi>Pointz</hi> and <hi>Minors</hi> would not take, then <hi>Smith</hi> began to make a ſhew of a pious intent, to make and erect a new foundation of that Schoole
<pb facs="tcp:14912:13"/> but yet in his owne name, and for his owne glory, whereby to outface and blindfold the world, that his former practices for ſupplanting thereof might not be ſeene. And to that purpoſe indowed the Schoole with<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Confeſſed in</hi> Smiths <hi>Decree in Chancery,</hi> Sect. 41. num. ibid. 13.</note> 12. pound Rent <hi>per annu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> out of her poſſeſſions of 300. pound <hi>per annum</hi> all being in the hand of him and his Leſſees. And for divulging of that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled pietie and bounty therein, ordeyned 25. Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offees for eſtabliſhing of that his new falſe foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Schoole and poſſeſſions, wherein hee had not, nor hath any intereſt lawfull at all.</p>
               <p n="25">25. That <hi>Smith</hi> (knowing his owne guiltineſſe) doubted that one <hi>Prichard,</hi> then as Maſter of that Schoole, placed there by <hi>Smith</hi> did incline to the aſſiſtance of <hi>Crokey</hi> for righting the Schoole, And in that doubt <hi>Smith</hi> ſet<note n="q" place="margin">Witneſſes.</note> vpon <hi>Prichard</hi> with diuers high and threatening ſpeaches, and warned <hi>Prichard</hi> that at a certaine day by <hi>Smith</hi> peremptorily prefix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Prichard</hi> ſhould depart from the Schoole as a profeſſed maintainer thereof againſt <hi>Smith,</hi> or elſe that <hi>Prichard</hi> muſt expect to be by <hi>Smith</hi> thrown out by violence, inſomuch that (vpon <hi>Prichards</hi> ſligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of <hi>Smiths</hi> threatenings) <hi>Smith</hi> (in outragious &amp; violent manner being accompanied with ſome 20<note n="r" place="margin">Witneſſes.</note> men) came to the Schoole and threatened to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyle the Schoole-houſe, and to throw <hi>Prichard</hi> out if hee would not preſently depart, and by thoſe meanes, and by frighting <hi>Prichards</hi> wife (being then in childe-bed) <hi>Prichard</hi> was inforced to leaue the Schoole to <hi>Smith,</hi> and ſo vpon compoſition left it.</p>
               <p n="26">26. That <hi>Crokey</hi> moued the Lord Chancellor for a third Commiſſion vpon the ſaid Certificate from three of the Commiſſioners in the ſaid ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, which notwithſtanding, and though <hi>Crokey</hi> had obtained diuers Commiſſions before, yet upon <hi>Smithes</hi> vntrue ſuggeſtions and like practices, it was
<pb facs="tcp:14912:14"/> ſo ordered the<note n="ſ" place="margin">Order.</note> 16. of Iune <hi>Anno</hi> 17. <hi>Regni regis Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobi,</hi> that thereby <hi>Crokey</hi> was not onely debarred for obtaining any further Commiſſion in behalfe of the Schoole, but alſo thereby diſgraced, and all his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings therein as much as might be; and <hi>Crokey</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo ſtopped and preiudiced) petitioned his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie to referre the finall hearing and determining the cauſe for the Schoole to the Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> the Lords Biſhops of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Winton,</hi> and to the Lord <hi>Hobart,</hi> or to any 3. or 2. of them, whereupon his Maieſtie was gratiouſly pleaſed, that the ſaid Lords ſhould take the contents of the ſaid Petition into their ſpeciall conſideration, and after hearing &amp; examining all particulars incident there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, ſhould make report in writing vnto his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie what they ſhould finde fitting to be done, aſwell for awarding ſuch a Commiſſion as was petitioned for, as for the certefying and determining the whole cauſe according to Iuſtice and good conſcience; as by the ſaid Petition and<note n="t" place="margin">Petition and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference.</note> Reference ſignified by Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary <hi>Naunton</hi> of the 24. of Iune 1619. appeareth, which Reference <hi>Crokey</hi> diligently proſecuted, but <hi>Smith</hi> would not by any meanes appeare before the Committees aſſigned by that Reference, vntill <hi>Crokey</hi> had procured foure ſeuerall<note n="u" place="margin">The Warrants.</note> Warrants, <hi>Smith</hi> well knowing that <hi>Crokey</hi> had brought vp to <hi>London</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny<note n="*" place="margin">Witneſſes.</note> Witneſſes, ſome of whom 100. miles diſtant from thence to his great trouble and charge; and that <hi>Crokey</hi> had them in a readineſſe the firſt day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the ſaid committees, and had feed his Councell diuers times therein for the better informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Lordſhips in the behalfe of the Schoole.</p>
               <p n="27">27. That vpon the fourth Warrant <hi>Smith</hi> appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and the cauſe vpon the ſaid Reference came to be heard before the Lord Archbiſhop, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:14912:14"/> 2. Lords Biſhops; &amp; vpon opening the cauſe; &amp; arguments and proofes before their Lordſhips made by the Councell on both ſides, their Lordſhips<note n="x" place="margin">Certificate.</note> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified his late Maieſtie of the powerfulnes &amp; indirect practices of <hi>Smith</hi> for getting the inheritance of all the Schoole lands worth 300. pound <hi>per annum</hi> for 5. pound<note n="y" place="margin">Certificate.</note> In which Certificate their Lordſhips held fit, that <hi>Crokey</hi> ſhould petition the Lord Chanceilor, for a third Commiſſion to ſettle the ſaid Schoole in her ancient eſtate <hi>Crokey</hi> accordingly Petitioned, and therevpon obtained an Order<note n="z" place="margin">Order.</note> in Chancery of the 21. of Ferbruary, <hi>Anno <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Regni regis Iacobi,</hi> that a Commiſſion ſhould be awarded to the Biſhops of Gloceſter and Briſtoll and others: Whereupon <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>key</hi> laboured for another Commiſſion according to the ſaid Order, but could nor prauaile vntill he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained to the Parliament, which was about 16. mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths after the ſaid Order, and then he obtained ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note n="a" place="margin">Order in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion which was duly executed as more particularly appeareth in the 37. Section of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</p>
               <p n="28">28. That <hi>Crokeyes</hi> Tryall vpon the ſaid Leaſe of Eiectment by <hi>Smithes</hi> indirect dealing, was delayed 4. yeares and<note n="b" place="margin">Copy of the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict and Iudgement.</note> more, but after that delay it was try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the Common pleas Barre, <hi>viz.</hi> in Eaſter Terme <hi>Anno</hi> 18. <hi>Regni regis Iacobi,</hi> though <hi>Smith</hi> ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly laboured by himſelfe and others to haue auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that Tryall, and <hi>Smith</hi> then laboured to ſeduce the ſaid <hi>Bodham Crokeyes</hi> Leſſee to<note n="c" place="margin">Witneſſes.</note> releaſe, vpon which Tryall, the matter was ſo ſtrongly defended by <hi>Smithes</hi> Councell, that the Tryall continued from 9. in the morning to 1. in the afternoone, which was by reaſon <hi>Smith</hi> and his Councell ſtood ſo mainely and ſo confidently vpon his ſaid ſeuerall bad tytles and practices.</p>
               <p n="29">29. That at that Tryall the Lord <hi>Hobart</hi> and the
<pb facs="tcp:14912:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> reſt of the Iudges of that Court vſed all good and iuſt endeuours for diſcouering of the truth whereby <hi>Smithes</hi> bad tytles (ſo ſtrongly vrged and inſiſted vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) were confuted, which <hi>Smith</hi> perceiuing, and that the Tryall muſt needs paſſe againſt him, and thereby all his practices come to light, and bee brought to naught to his vtter diſgrace and infamy: <hi>Smith</hi> cryed<note n="d" place="margin">Witneſſes.</note> out with a lowd voyce in moſt earneſt and pittifull manner to the Iudges that he was vndone, if they would not haue compaſſion on him, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all beſought them in all he might to draw <hi>Crokey</hi> to ſome compoſition, or to referre the cauſe to them: Whereupon the Iudges in compaſſion of <hi>Smith</hi> ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly moued <hi>Crokey</hi> to referre the matter to them, but <hi>Crokey</hi> refuſed ſo to doe, telling the Iudges that the cauſe concerned the Schoole more than him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and for which he had vndertaken, and was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged both in his duty to God, for the common good, and by his profeſſion to his late Maieſtie, the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and others; And theſe motions by <hi>Smith</hi> to the Iudges, and the Iudges to <hi>Crokey</hi> were betweene the time of the Iuries going from the Barre, and giuing vp their verdict which was not giuen vp vntill the next morning, and then it paſſed for<note n="e" place="margin">Copy of the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict and Iudgement.</note> 
                  <hi>Crokeyes</hi> ſaid Leſſee.</p>
               <p n="30">30. That a day or two after the virdict, <hi>Crokey</hi> by his Councell moued the Court for Iudgement and poſſeſſion according to the aforeſaid verdict and Rules, made by the aſſent of <hi>Smith</hi> and his Councell as aforeſaid, which Rules and verdict notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and notwithſtanding alſo the 4. yeares delay and more of that Tryall by <hi>Smithes</hi> meanes, and the Statutes of Ieofaile made 32. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>C.</hi> 30. 2. <hi>Edw:</hi> 6. <hi>C.</hi> 32. 18. <hi>Eliz. C.</hi> 13. by which (as <hi>Crokey</hi> conceiued) <hi>Smith</hi> was debarred from vſing any further delay af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Verdict, yet <hi>Smith</hi> (ſtill p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſecuting his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity
<pb facs="tcp:14912:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the Iudges, and vpon his falſe ſuggeſtions to them) was permitted to ſpeake in areſt of Iudgement, whereby <hi>Crokey</hi> was delayed both the Eaſter and Trinity Termes next after the Verdict, and the ſaid Leaſe of Eiectment (which was for 5. yeares) being then well-nigh expired, <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>key</hi> in the latter end of Auguſt then next following<note n="f" place="margin">Copy of the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and direction.</note> Peticioned his Maieſtie for his Maieſties direction to the Iudges in that behalfe, whereupon his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie was pleaſed to ſignifie his pleaſure by Sir <hi>Iohn Sucklyn</hi> then Maſter of Requeſts 3. Sept. 1620. which was, that the Lord <hi>Hobart,</hi> and the reſt of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Iudges of the Common pleas ſhould cauſe the ſaid Rules of the ſaid Court, ſo made in open Court by conſent of both parties, to be performed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the true intent and meaning of the ſame; In regard the Leaſe for tryall of the tytle in the premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes made to the ſaid <hi>Bodham,</hi> was that moneth of September to expire. Which directions from his Maieſtie <hi>Crokey</hi> preſented to the Lord <hi>Hobart</hi> before the expiration of the ſaid Leaſe for the eiectment, which Directions notwithſtanding, &amp; notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding alſo the ſaid Rules, and the Statutes of Ieofaile &amp; 4. yeares delay, before the ſaid Tryall, <hi>Crokey</hi> could not obtaine Iudgement, vntill the ſaid Leaſe for Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of the Tytle was expired, and then Iudgement was awarded; But the ſaid Leaſe being by the ſaid delayes worne out, <hi>Crokey</hi> could not by Law haue any Writ for poſſeſſion according to the ſaid Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict Rules, and his Maieſties moſt gratious Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and intention in that beholfe ſo ſignified, or the ſaid Statutes of Ieofaile; All which delay and ſtay of iudgement, ſeeming onely to be but vpon a meere ſuggeſtion by <hi>Smith,</hi> which<note n="g" place="margin">Affedauit to proue <hi>Tippets</hi> name ſo to be.</note> was that one of the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors names called <hi>Tippets</hi> was miſtaken, and in the Record written <hi>Tripets,</hi> and though <hi>Crokey</hi> did
<pb facs="tcp:14912:16"/> often during that delay of Iudgement offer to<note n="h" place="margin">Witneſſes.</note> proue, and to produce the Record to ſhew the contrary, and in the end did proue ſo much.</p>
               <p n="31">31. That during the ſaid delay of Iudgement, and betweene the ſaid Verdict and Iudgement <hi>Smith</hi> (to croſſe all former proceedings of the Schoole and the Verdict) vpon diuers vntrue ſuggeſtions compi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in a Petition to his late Maieſtie procured a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference from his Maieſtie ſignified by Sir <hi>Sidney Mountagu</hi> Maſter of Requeſts 25. <hi>Iunij</hi> 1620. The effect of which Petition and Reference;<note n="i" place="margin">Copy of the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Reference.</note> As alſo <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keys</hi> Anſwere thereunto next follow, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">NVM.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">PETITION.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">ANSVVERE.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1.</cell>
                        <cell>That a Tryall in Eaſter Terme <hi>anno</hi> 1620. was had in the Common Pleas, in an action of <hi>eiectione firme</hi> brought againſt <hi>Smith,</hi> by <hi>Thomas Bodham</hi> Leſſee to <hi>Crokey</hi> for a meſſuage and 50. Acres of land in <hi>North-Nib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> in the County of Gloceſter, parcell of the Poſſeſſions of the ſaid Schoole, wherein <hi>Crokey</hi> claymed a Leaſe for 12. yeares.</cell>
                        <cell>1. <hi>It is true that ſuch an Action was brought, but it was laid for the ſaid Meſſuage and</hi> 130. <hi>acres and a Mill, as before was layd by</hi> Smith <hi>himſelfe in his Informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oon for Champerty brought in the Common pleas, for which Crokey hath offered proofe,</hi> Sect. 15. <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keyes tytle was for</hi> 21. <hi>years when hee made his firſt entry before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, and ſo offered to be proued,</hi> Sect. 12.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2.</cell>
                        <cell>That <hi>Smith</hi> had againſt the ſaid Tytle Verdicts, and Non-ſuites at Law, and Decrees, and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions in Chancery.</cell>
                        <cell>2. <hi>That this is moſt vntrue will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by that which</hi> Crokey <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the</hi> 14. Sect. <hi>hath truely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3.</cell>
                        <cell>That at the laſt Tryal <hi>Crokey</hi> had vrged vntruly &amp; impertinently, that <hi>Smith</hi> had indirectly ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured the ſuppreſſing of the Schoole, and ſought to conuert</cell>
                        <cell>3. <hi>That</hi> Crokey <hi>in this vrged no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but truth, is manifeſtly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued before in diuers places of this his Relation: But it will appeare more plainly in</hi> Crokeys <hi>Anſwer</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14912:16"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>the poſſeſſions thereof to his owne priuate benefit.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>to the Decree mentioned</hi> Sect. 41. Numero decreti 19.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4.</cell>
                        <cell>That <hi>Smith</hi> (not hauing infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med his Councell in that point being no way pertinent to the iſſue) <hi>Crokey</hi> obtained a Verdict againſt <hi>Smith,</hi> wherin no Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was then entred.</cell>
                        <cell>4. Smith <hi>had informed his Councell in all things, but vſed all meanes poſsible to ſtay Iudgement, of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to weare out the Leaſe made for tryall of the Tytle, or to bring</hi> Crokey <hi>to a compoſition, as before is truly ſet forth.</hi> Sect. 29. 30. 31. 32. &amp; 33.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5.</cell>
                        <cell>That <hi>Smith</hi> was able to proue he had beene ſo farre from wronging the Schoole, as that he had done many acts to his great charge for pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſeruing of it, and had bought in tytles that might haue troubled it, and was ready to eſtabliſh the Schoole in ſuch ſort as ſhould be fit.</cell>
                        <cell>5. <hi>The whole tract of this Relation and proofes proue this to bee very falſe, and that</hi> Smith <hi>hath ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured as much as in him lay to make good to himſelfe all thoſe bad and feigned tytles againſt the Schoole and for that purpoſe did many acts, and thoſe moſt vilde and vnconſcionable, for an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cling whereof,</hi> vide Sect. 40. Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero Decreti, 19.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6.</cell>
                        <cell>Wherefore and for acquitall of his reputation, and for ſetling a finall end betweene <hi>Smith</hi> and <hi>Crokey,</hi> and for auoydance of multiplicity of ſuites and other inconueniences likely to ariſe, deſired that the conſideration thereof might be referred either to the Iudges of the Common Pleas, or to ſuch others as his Maieſtie ſhould thinke beſt for ſuch end and order as ſhould be fit.</cell>
                        <cell>6. Smithes <hi>backe being at wall, and all his plots and deuiſes being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered, and when no better would be, he now to ſaue his repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, makes a great ſhew of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, his ayme being by ſome compromiſe to take off</hi> Crokey <hi>from further proſecution for the Schoole, which was laboured as much as might be, but all in vaine, for</hi> Crokey <hi>had then, and ſtill is reſolued (by Gods grace) to right both the Schoole and himſelfe, that neither may be ſubiect to</hi> Smithes <hi>gins or deuotion.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:14912:17"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7.</cell>
                        <cell>That his Maieſties pleaſure was, that the Iudges of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Pleas taking conſideration of the Petition, ſhould call the ſaid partyes before them, and thereupon take order to ſettle the ſtate of the Schoole, and for auoyding of further ſuites to compoſe the differences of the ſaid partyes if they could.</cell>
                        <cell>7. Crokey <hi>obſerued his Maieſties Reference in all things.</hi>
                           <p>
                              <hi>But</hi> Smith <hi>laboured the contrary as may well appeare by the vſe hee made of this his Maieſties gratious intention, which was to ſettle the Schoole according to the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and to right</hi> Crokey, <hi>and not to alter the ſame, or to preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice</hi> Crokey, <hi>and ſo his Maieſtie before had declared by the ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Sir</hi> Daniel Dun, <hi>Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary</hi> Naunton, <hi>and Sir</hi> Iohn Sucklyn.</p>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p n="32">32. That <hi>Smith</hi> vſed the ſaid Petition and Refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the intent aforeſaid, and as an Inſtrument to moue the Lord <hi>Hobart</hi> further to preſſe <hi>Crokey</hi> to a compoſition, and to delay the Iudgement, and ſo it came to paſſe, for at the hearing vpon <hi>Smithes</hi> ſaid Petition and his Maieſties Reference thereupon, the Lord <hi>Hobart</hi> preſſed <hi>Crokey</hi> to referre the matter to him and the other Iudges of that Court, which <hi>Crokey</hi> refuſing could not obtaine Iudgement (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is ſaid) vntill the Leaſe was expired, and then obtained Iudgement, but no poſſeſſion notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſaid Rules Verdict, and his Maieſties ſaid expreſſe directtions for the ſame: But <hi>Smith</hi> procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red one <hi>Gayre</hi> one of Maſter <hi>Brownlows</hi> Clerkes to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſaid Rules of Court, by razing and interly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the<note n="k" place="margin">Rules.</note> Record; Whereupon, and vpon proofe made and <hi>Gayres</hi> confeſſion in Court, the Lord <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bart</hi> and that Court committed <hi>Smith</hi> to the Fleete, for not yeelding poſſeſſion. But <hi>Smith</hi> ſhortly after obtained his libertie, and ſo was at large vntill <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>key</hi> complained that <hi>Smith</hi> had not yeelded poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:14912:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> according to the ſaid Rules, whereupon <hi>Smith</hi> was committed againe, but ſhortly after was releaſed without performing the ſaid Rules, and ſo <hi>Crokey</hi> cannot obtaine poſſeſſion to this day.</p>
               <p n="33">33. That ſhortly after the Tryall vpon <hi>Smiths</hi> ſaid Petition and his Maieſties ſaid Reference thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (<hi>viz.</hi> in Michaelmaſſe Terme <hi>Anno Regni regis Iae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobi</hi> 18.) his Maieſties Attourney<note n="l" place="margin">Decree hereafter. following, <hi>Sect. 41</hi>
                  </note> Generall by di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rection of the Lord <hi>Hobart,</hi> exhibited an Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Chancery againſt <hi>Smith</hi> and <hi>Crokey,</hi> thereby ſuppoſing a confederacy<note n="m" place="margin">Order.</note> between <hi>Smith</hi> and <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>key</hi> to take away or peruert the poſſeſſions of the ſaid Schoole, and to ſupplant the ſame. To which Information <hi>Crokey</hi> anſwered,<note n="n" place="margin">Crokeys <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</hi>
                  </note> and thereby cleared himſelfe of that ſuggeſtion, vtterly diſclayming all other intereſt in or to the Schoole or Lands other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then by his ſaid right to <hi>Warrens</hi> Court, and his zeale for preſeruation of the ſaid Schoole and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions thereto belonging, and withall by his ſaid Anſwer charged <hi>Smith</hi> with his ſeuerall practices a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Schoole, and thereby alſo ſhewed in how many caſes he had defended the ſaid Schoole againſt <hi>Smith</hi> and others, that had gone about to ſupplant it. But <hi>Smith</hi> by his<note n="o" place="margin">Smithes <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
                  </note> Anſwer to the ſaid Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſet forth all his bad tytles herein before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and thereto added many vntrue ſuggeſtions, howbeit vpon the ſaid Information <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> an<note n="p" place="margin">Order Iniunction.</note> Iniunction againſt <hi>Crokey,</hi> and thereby ſtopped all <hi>Crokeys</hi> proceedings in Law or Chancery in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of the Schoole, or in his owne behalfe euer ſince againſt <hi>Smith,</hi> which Iniunction <hi>Smith</hi> himſelfe ſerued upon <hi>Crokey,</hi> and which <hi>Crokey</hi> obeying, <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>key</hi> forbore any further proceeding in Law, or Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery in that behalfe; and by that meanes all <hi>Crokeys</hi> endeuours which he had ſo faithfully, and zealouſly followed in behalfe of the Schoole were vtterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated,
<pb facs="tcp:14912:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> contrary to his Maieſties ſaid directions, and contrary to the Honourable and Charitable ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours of the ſaid Lord Archbiſhop, the Lord Chancellour, and of the Lords Biſhops of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Winton.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="34">34. That vpon the motion<note n="q" place="margin">Confeſſed <hi>Smiths</hi> Decree in Chancery. Lord <hi>Hobarts</hi> War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant.</note> of Maſter Attorney Generall (according to the direction of the Lord <hi>Hobart</hi>) the Lord Chancellour awarded a Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion vpon the Statute of Charitable vſes, leauing the nomination of the Commiſſioners to the Lord <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bart,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Witneſſes,</note> who nominated Commiſſioners, <hi>Crokey</hi> not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting thereunto, But that Commiſſion (though ſealed) was neuer put in execution, for the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was then at hand.</p>
               <p n="35">
                  <note place="margin">Not to be denyed.</note>35. That <hi>Smith</hi> procured himſelfe to be made a Burgeſſe in that Parliament for <hi>Midhurſt</hi> in the County of Suſſex 130. miles diſtant from his reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and this was <hi>anno</hi> 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</p>
               <p n="36">36. That neuertheleſſe <hi>Crokey</hi> preſented a Bill<note n="r" place="margin">Bill in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> in that Parliament againſt <hi>Smith</hi> on behalfe of the Schoole, and thereupon obtained an<note n="ſ" place="margin">Order in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> order of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament for another Commiſſion vpon the Statute of charitable (vſes ſo long before ſought for by <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>key</hi>) to inquire according to the Statute of Charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vſes, and withall ordered that the Lords Biſhops of Worceſter and Gloceſter and Briſtoll, and their Chancellours, and others ſhould bee Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</p>
               <p n="37">
                  <note place="margin">Witneſſes.</note>37. That <hi>Crokey</hi> ſued forth that Commiſſion, and going on in the execution thereof, and hauing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> before had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> loſſes, at Sea and other wayes, and <hi>Crokey</hi> being indebted to one <hi>Auguſtine Haruy</hi> 50. pound, for which <hi>Haruy</hi> had <hi>Crokeyes</hi> Bond of 100. pound, <hi>Crokey</hi> was arreſted vpon that Bond, and detained, and when <hi>Crokey</hi> offered to<note n="t" place="margin">Witneſſes.</note> ſatisfie the debt <hi>Haruy</hi> had made ouer that Bond to one <hi>Aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14912:18"/> &amp; <hi>Haruy,</hi> and <hi>Aſhman</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">Order declaring the ſame.</note> together, had made ouer the ſame to one <hi>Fiſher,</hi> and ſo <hi>Crokey</hi> could not know with whom to deale, which intricaſie (as it ſeemeth, and as <hi>Crokey</hi> is verily perſwaded) came by the meanes of <hi>Smith,</hi> or ſome of his Agents and confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates, for that <hi>Smith</hi> had before by himſelfe and others his confederates dealt with others of <hi>Crokeys</hi> Creditors to buy<note n="*" place="margin">Witneſſes.</note> 
                  <hi>Crokeys</hi> debts, and <hi>Crokey</hi> is the rather ſo perſwaded, for that at the time <hi>Crokey</hi> was ſo arreſted, one <hi>Bird</hi> (whom <hi>Smith</hi> hath long vſed and imployed in his affaires) and one <hi>Archer</hi> a ſeruant of <hi>Smithes</hi> were at that his arreſt, and for that alſo <hi>Smith</hi> hath beene very inquiſitiue to know what matters were againſt <hi>Crokey</hi> in the Kings Bench, and for that alſo <hi>Crokey</hi> hath ſince endeuoured by all meanes to giue ſatisfaction whereby to releaſe himſelfe but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not,<note place="margin">Orders of the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery.</note> as may appeare by that which immediatly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth; For <hi>Crokey</hi> when he had ſo offered ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and was notwithſtanding ſo put off, and ſued at Law in the name of <hi>Haruy, Crokey</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menſed a ſuite in Chancery againſt <hi>Haruy</hi> and <hi>Aſhman</hi> in point of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, &amp; there <hi>Crokey</hi> hauing obtained an<note n="x" place="margin">An Iniunction vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Seale.</note> Iniuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſtay the ſaid ſuit at Law, <hi>Haruy</hi> &amp; the reſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any notice to <hi>Crokey,</hi> or any for him by vntrue ſuggeſtions obtained a<note n="y" place="margin">Affedauit.</note> Report, and ſo the cauſe was diſmiſſed and that Iniunction was diſſolued, and which was at the very time when <hi>Haruy</hi> or <hi>Aſhman</hi> ſhould haue ſhewed cauſe, why they ſhould not haue accepted the 50. pound<note n="z" place="margin">Order.</note> principall. Whereupon <hi>Crokey</hi> vpon his Petition obtained a<note n="a" place="margin">Petition Refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</note> Reference from his Maieſtie <hi>anno</hi> 1620. to Sir <hi>Edm: Boyer,</hi> and Sir <hi>George Paul</hi> Knights to mediate, but <hi>Haruie</hi> though<note n="b" place="margin">Affedauit.</note> ſerued with their Warrant would not appeare; Vpon that <hi>Crokey</hi> obtained an<note n="c" place="margin">Iniunction vnder Seale.</note> Iniuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Court of Requeſts for ſtay of <hi>Haruies</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings at Law which <hi>Haruy</hi> alſo contemned and
<pb facs="tcp:14912:19"/> proceeded to a Iudgement, <hi>Crokey</hi> vpon that obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a<note n="d" place="margin">Protection.</note> Protection of the Parliament; At which time <hi>Crokey</hi> going on in the execution of the ſaid Commiſſion ſo awarded by order in Parliament was notwithſtanding his ſaid Protection taken<note n="e" place="margin">Witneſſes.</note> in Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution when the Iudges were gone their Circuit, and the Parliament proroged. And the ſaid debt being ſo made ouer, <hi>Crokey</hi> was ſo intangled, as that when <hi>Crokey</hi> and his friends tendered the whole hundred pounds, and 7. pound more for coſts for his releaſe of impriſonment, no other matter being againſt him no penny would be accepted, and ſo <hi>Crokey</hi> lay fiue moneths in Priſon vntill the Parliament ſate againe, and then Petitioning to<note n="f" place="margin">Petition to the Parliament and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge.</note> the Parliament, was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed. And all this trouble came vpon <hi>Crokey</hi> when he was to haue followed that Commiſſion ſo awar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by order in Parliament and by <hi>Smithes</hi> meanes, as <hi>Crokey</hi> is verily perſwaded for the reaſons afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; yet did not <hi>Crokey</hi> neglect that Commiſſion, but to his great<note n="g" place="margin">Witneſſes.</note> charge of threeſcore pounds and vpward imployed others therein; And ſo the ſaid Commiſſion was executed at Gloceſter by the ſaid Biſhops and others, and an Inquiſition was found 19. <hi>Regni regis Iacobi</hi> by the oathes of 17. Iurors all ſubſtantiall and men of good eſtates of the County of Gloceſter. Whereupon the ſaid Commiſſioners returned the ſaid Commiſſion and<note n="h" place="margin">Copies of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, Inquiſition, Certificate and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree.</note> Inquiſition, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with their Decree and Certificate thereupon, the ſame being Dated 19. September <hi>Anno Regni re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis Iacobi</hi> 19. which ſaid Certificate and Decree was to the effect following, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="decree_summary">
                           <p>
                              <hi>That there appeared before them aſwell the ſaid Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, as alſo diuers Tenants of the ſaid Schoole lands and diuers Witneſſes to teſtifie on either ſide: As alſo</hi> Crokey <hi>the proſecutor on behalfe of the ſaid Schoole by his
<pb facs="tcp:14912:19"/> Councell on the one part: And the ſaid</hi> Smith <hi>claiming the inheritance of the lands belonging to the ſaid Schoole on the other part. Which ſaid</hi> Smith <hi>at the firſt tooke diuers exceptions againſt the proceedings vpon the ſaid Commiſsion, but afterwards did then and there wayue and relinquiſh all the ſame and all other exceptions whatſoeuer in that behalfe, and conſented that the ſaid Commiſsioners ſhould proceed to Tryall of the right, whereupon there was giuen in euidence to the Iury the ſaid</hi> 3. <hi>Grants of the</hi> 16. <hi>of Iune</hi> Anno 7. Regni regis Ricardi 2. <hi>of the</hi> 1. <hi>of Iuly</hi> Anno 8. Ricardi 2. <hi>and of the</hi> 20. <hi>October</hi> Anno 8. Ricardi 2. <hi>as in the</hi> 2. 3. 4. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are mentioned; and alſo an Inquiſition vpon an</hi> Ad quod Damnum <hi>as in the</hi> 1. <hi>Section is mentioned.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>That</hi> Smith <hi>ſhewed forth the ſaid Grant from his Maieſtie to him and</hi> Gulſton <hi>made as in the</hi> 17. <hi>Section. and</hi> Smith <hi>then confeſſed that the lands therein mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned were the ſame that were giuen as aforeſaid to the Schoole, and that</hi> Smith <hi>then ſhewed forth alſo an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplification of a Bill, Anſwer, and Depoſitions in the ſaid ſuite brought by</hi> Biſhop (<hi>before mentioned in the</hi> 17. <hi>Section, and that thereby and by diuers other wayes</hi> Smith <hi>earneſtly endeuoured to proue that the ſaid Schoole lands were giuen to his Maieſtie by the ſaid Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of</hi> 1. Edward 6. <hi>as Chantry and concealed lands.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>That it was inferred by the Councell on the Schooles behalfe. That the ſaid ſuite was but a meere practice of</hi> Smith <hi>to draw the ſaid foundation within the ſaid Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of Chantries; and that there was further ſhewed to the ſaid Commiſsioners and Iury, a Certificate ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by the Lord Archbiſhop of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>and by the Lords Biſhops of</hi> London <hi>and</hi> Winton, <hi>wherein the ſaid</hi> Smiths <hi>practices for ſuppreſsion of the Schoole</hi> inter alia <hi>are mentioned.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>That againſt which euidence for the Schoole</hi> Smiths <hi>Councell then vrged and gaue in euidence a Copy of the
<pb facs="tcp:14912:20"/> Ordinances and Statutes mentioned to be made touching the due gouernment of the ſaid Schoole and of the lands wherewith the ſame was indowed, and that amongſt the ſaid Ordinances</hi> Smithes <hi>Councell ſtood eſpecially vpon that Ordinance: That the Maſter of that Schoole for the time being, ſhould bee a Prieſt and celebrate for the Founders of the ſchoole. And others in the ſaid Ordinance, named after their departure hence, and whereupon it was earneſtly vrged by</hi> Smithes <hi>Councell, that foraſmuch as in the deed of foundation. the Lands were giuen to the Maſter and two poore Schollers and their Succeſſors, to their aide and ſuſtentation according to the Ordinances, to be made by the ſaid</hi> Walter, Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam, <hi>and</hi> Katherine, <hi>that therefore the foundation of the Schoole and Lands was within the ſaid Statute of</hi> 1. Edward 6.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>For anſwere whereunto there was ſhewed forth the opinions of Sir</hi> Henry Yelverton <hi>then Attourney Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and Sir</hi> Thomas Couentry <hi>then Solicitor to the contrary, and that it was then further anſwered on the Schooles behalfe, that the ſaid Grants and Licences of the foundation, donation, and</hi> Ad quod Damnum <hi>were abſolute to the charitable vſes therein expreſſed, without any mention of any ſuperſtitious vſe at all, and that therein there was no relation to any Ordinances to be made but onely in the</hi> Habendum, <hi>whoſe proper Office is to expreſſe the eſtate; And that therefore the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ought to extend onely to order the Succeſsion, and not to make a new vſe, ſeruice or conſideration. Beſides, it then appeared that the ſaid Ordinances were made long before the foundation of the ſaid Schoole, and therefore of little regard. And that it was then alſo informed that the ſaid Schoole and the Maſter, and two poore Schollers in the ſame, had continually beene maintained according to the ſaid firſt foundation, vntill within</hi> 16. <hi>yeares laſt paſt, which was not denyed by</hi> Smith <hi>or his Councell.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <pb facs="tcp:14912:20"/>
                           <p>
                              <hi>That thereupon the ſaid Commiſsioners were and are of opinion, that the ſaid Lands ought to be reſtored, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſaid charitable and pious foundation which continued</hi> 100. <hi>yeares before the ſaid Statute of</hi> Edward 6. <hi>and almoſt</hi> 60. <hi>yeares after, before it was queſtioned. And therefore according to the ſaid Statute of charitable vſes, and the ſaid Commiſsion to them di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected; They did adiudge and decree, that the ſaid Lands ſhould be reſtored and imployed to the vſe of the ſaid Schoole, according to the ſaid firſt foundation. But for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as the ſaid Corporation was of late diſcontinued, and the Patronage of the ſaid Schoole is claimed by</hi> Smith, <hi>and was before in queſtion, whereof the ſaid Commiſsioners could not determine. And</hi> Crokey <hi>clai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth a Leaſe of a Tenement parcell of the ſaid Schoole lands, whereof as they were informed,</hi> Crokey <hi>hath a Verdict and Iudgement againſt</hi> Smith, <hi>but cannot (as they were informed, by reaſon</hi> Smith <hi>was a Burgeſſe of the Parliament) obtaine an execution thereof, and hath (as they were alſo informed) exhauſted and ſpent his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate in the proſecution, and deſired recompence for his great charges therein, they could not adiudge, therefore the ſame, they humbly referred to the conſideration and direction of the Court of Chancery or of the Parliament, to which (as they were informed)</hi> Crokey <hi>had preferred his Bill for further therein to be done. So as by the ſaid Certificate &amp; Decree it may plainly appeare, that the ſame Commiſsion was not executed partially or at randon, but equally and iuſtly, and whereto</hi> Smith <hi>and his Councell there preſent conſented, and thereby</hi> Smith <hi>concluded himſelfe,</hi> Crokey <hi>then being abſent.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p n="38">38. That ſhortly after the returne of the ſaid Commiſſion ſo executed as aforeſaid by direction of the Parliament and Inquiſition, Certificate and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree; thereupon <hi>Smith,</hi> (perceiuing that the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was ſoone after to be diſſolued) notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:14912:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> he had formerly wayued all exceptions to the aforeſaid Inquiſition, Certificate and Decree, which is by the ſaid Commiſſioners certified as aforeſaid, yet <hi>Smith</hi> vpon the ending of that Parliament, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained an<note n="i" place="margin">Order. Exceptions. <hi>Crokeys</hi> Anſwer to thoſe Exceptions.</note> Order in Chancery of the 3. of December, to put in new exceptions to the ſaid Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ſaid proceedings, which <hi>Crokey</hi> in defence of the Schoole anſwered. And the Parliament (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then ended) <hi>Crokey</hi> applyed himſelfe to the Chancery for a day of hearing, not doubting a confirmation of the ſaid Inquiſition, Certificate and Decree, which day of hearing after much labour <hi>Crokey</hi> obtained, And ſo the cauſe was by the Lord Keeper ordered<note n="k" place="margin">Order.</note> to be heard before his Lordſhip and Iuſtice <hi>Hutton,</hi> wherewith <hi>Crokey</hi> was well ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, but when the cauſe came to bee heard, Iuſtice <hi>Chamberlaine</hi> who married with the Lady <hi>Berkley (Smith</hi> being her chiefe Steward) in ſtead of Iuſtice <hi>Hutton</hi> ſate in Court, and ſo the cauſe was heard<note n="l" place="margin">Order.</note> 17. Iuly <hi>anno</hi> 20. <hi>Regni regis Iacobi.</hi> At which hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Smithes</hi> exceptions were argued, and being found friuolous, no reſolution was thereupon, yet was not the ſaid Decree ſo made by the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners in that Commiſſion vpon the Statute of charitable vſes confirmed, as <hi>Crokey</hi> expected; but at that time the Lord Keeper granted<note n="m" place="margin">Order.</note> another Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion vpon that Information which was exhibited by Maſter Attourney Generall two yeares before not proſecuted, by reaſon the ſame cauſe was exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Crokey</hi> in a Bill to the Parliament, where the ſame was<note n="n" place="margin">Order in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> ordered and proceeded vpon, as before is ſaid, Sect. 36. Which proceeding laſt ſpoken of in Chancery, quite tooke away all <hi>Crokeys</hi> proſecution for the Schoole a ſecond time. And in which Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion diuers of <hi>Smiths</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Witneſſes.</note> friends were made Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, ſome of whom had declared themſelues
<pb facs="tcp:14912:21"/> open oppoſors of the Schoole, and <hi>Crokey</hi> by their demenour againſt the due execution of former Commiſſions ſued out by <hi>Crokey</hi> in the behalfe of the Schoole, which Commiſſioners <hi>Crokey</hi> much<note n="p" place="margin">Witneſſes, Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Anſwer.</note> laboured both by Petition and motion in Court to haue altered, but could not therein preuaile. And yet the Lord Keeper at that hearing very ſharply re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued <hi>Smith</hi> plainely telling him that he had left no practice vnatempted to ſupplant the Schoole as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is true.</p>
               <p n="39">39. That <hi>Smith</hi> (going on with that Commiſſion vpon the ſaid Information) practiced againe with <hi>Haxuy, Aſhman,</hi> and <hi>Fiſher,</hi> or ſome of them to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon <hi>Crokey</hi> a ſecond time for the ſaid debt of 50. pound, for which <hi>Crokey</hi> was before diſcharged by Parliament, whereupon <hi>Crokey</hi> commenced another ſuite in Chancery againſt <hi>Haruy</hi> and <hi>Fiſher.</hi> That cauſe was referred to Sir <hi>Iames Huſſey,</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">Report.</note> who repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that it was reaſonable <hi>Fiſher</hi> ſhould accept of the principall, which was 50. pound. which <hi>Fiſher</hi> refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, whereupon <hi>Crokey</hi> obtained a Warrant from the late Lord chiefe Iuſtice and others his Maieſties Commiſſioners appointed to heare the cauſes of Priſoners for their reliefe, directed to the ſaid <hi>Haruy</hi> and <hi>Fiſher</hi> for their appearauce before the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners for Priſoners; But the ſaid <hi>Haruy</hi> vpon the firſt ſummons appeared not, nor did <hi>Haruy</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare at all, but vpon the ſecond ſummons <hi>Fiſher</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared. And the cauſe being heard<note n="r" place="margin">Certificate of the Commiſſioners, and their opinions.</note> 
                  <hi>Fiſher</hi> would not conforme himſelfe to any order; Whereupon the Commiſſioners gaue him further day, and then appearing alſo, would by no meanes or mediation conforme himſelfe, but ſtood out in contempt of that Commiſſion, then affirming that he would haue the extremity of the Law againſt <hi>Crokey,</hi> and which the ſaid Commiſſioners haue<note n="r" place="margin">The ſame Certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficate.</note> certified, and of their
<pb facs="tcp:14912:22"/> opinions therein. And further, <hi>Fiſher</hi> gaue forth in ſpeeches, that he cared not for his debt, nor for the whole money vpon the Execution, for hee would make dice<note n="ſ" place="margin">Affedauit.</note> of <hi>Crokeys</hi> bones. And therefore, and for the reaſons aforeſaid declared in the 37. Section. <hi>Crokey</hi> is verily perſwaded, that <hi>Smith</hi> had his hand in all theſe matters betweene <hi>Crokey</hi> and <hi>Haruy, Aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> and <hi>Fiſher, Crokey</hi> doth know that one<note n="t" place="margin">Not to be denyed.</note> 
                  <hi>Farrer</hi> a Clerke in Chancery, was a chiefe Agent in this confederacie.</p>
               <p n="40">40. That the ſaid<note n="u" place="margin">Commiſſion. Order.</note> Commiſſion ſo awarded vpon the ſaid Information, did beare <hi>Teſte,</hi> 24. Iuly <hi>anno</hi> 20. <hi>Regni regis Iacobi,</hi> and was grounded vpon an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in Chancery of the 23. of Nouember. <hi>Anno Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni regis Iacobi</hi> 18. which was before the Parliament. And which Order was granted vpon his late Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Reference vpon <hi>Smiths</hi> Petition, wherein were diuers vntrue ſuggeſtions, as before Section 31. and which are alſo there anſwered. And that his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Reference vpon ſo falſe a petition, ſhould be ſo farre extended in the behalfe of <hi>Smith,</hi> that ſought to ſupplant the Schoole, and to doe all wrong, and that not onely his Maieſties former References, but alſo his ſeuerall directions vpon ſeuerall true Petitions preſented by <hi>Crokey</hi> in behalfe of the Schoole, and <hi>Crokey,</hi> before mentioned Section 20. 26. 30. ſhould be altogether neglected and ſlighted, as alſo the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections by Parliament betweene the time of the ſaid Order, and the time of the hearing (whereupon the ſaid Order of the 17. of Iuly, <hi>Anno</hi> 20. <hi>Regni regis Iacobi,</hi> which was ſome 22. months after) <hi>Crokey</hi> moſt humbly ſubmitteth himſelfe to the conſideration of his Maieſtie, and this high and Honourable aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly. And whether <hi>Smith</hi> in this buſineſſe hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his power, his ſubtilty, and vnconſcionable pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, and conſequently his abuſes both to his late
<pb facs="tcp:14912:22"/> Maieſtie, and his Magiſtrates and Iudges. For the manner of the execution of the laſt mentioned Commiſſion: It was as <hi>Crokey</hi> before imagined it would be, when he laboured to haue had an alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Commiſſioners names; But as to that <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>key</hi> hath fully ſpoken in his anſwer to the Decree, grounded vpon the ſaid Information and order of the 23. of Nouember, and vpon the ſaid laſt men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Commiſſion thereupon, Sect. 42. number 4.</p>
               <p n="41">41. That for diuers indirect practices and miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanours done by the ſaid <hi>Smith</hi> and his confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, tending to the ſupplanting and ouerthrow of the ſaid Schoole, <hi>Crokey</hi> (being incouraged by the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> who had well informed himſelfe of the cauſe on the behalfe of the Schoole) exhibited a Bill into the Starchamber againſt <hi>Smith</hi> and others, and ſerued <hi>Smith</hi> with a Subpena before the Parliament in <hi>anno</hi> 1619. But <hi>Smith</hi> hauing at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the place of a Burgeſſe in Parliament as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is ſaid, <hi>Crokey</hi> was delayed for the time of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, and long after (which was about 16. moneths) before <hi>Smith</hi> could be brought to Anſwer; In the end <hi>Smith</hi> anſwered. But ſo it was with <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>key,</hi> that by that delay of <hi>Smithes,</hi> and <hi>Smithes</hi> other ſaid practices together, <hi>Crokey</hi> was diſabled and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed in his eſtate, and impriſoned in manner and by <hi>Smithes</hi> meanes as aforeſaid, Sect. 37. And yet <hi>Crokey</hi> (hauing a conſtant care for reſtoring the ſaid Schoole and poſſeſſions thereof, and being deſirous to diſcouer the practices and miſdemeanours by <hi>Smith</hi> and his confederates, oppoſors, and declared enemies thereto ſet forth by and vpon his ſaid Bill in the Starchamber) tooke out 5. Subpenaes againſt the other Defendants. Dated 30. Ianuary, <hi>Anno Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni regis Iacobi</hi> 20. vpon which day the cauſe vpon the ſaid Information in Chancery came to be heard the
<pb facs="tcp:14912:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſecond time before the Lord Keeper, Iuſtice <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaine,</hi> and Iuſtice <hi>Iohnes</hi> Aſſiſtants. Whereupon the Court decreed not onely contrary to, and againſt the ſaid Commiſſion ſo awarded by Parliament vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Statute of charitable vſes, and againſt the ſaid Inquiſition, Certificate, and Decree, vpon the ſaid Commiſſion, but alſo againſt <hi>Crokeys</hi> particular right. At which hearing, <hi>Crokey</hi> was not admitted to produce any matter in behalfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of himſelfe, but was inioyned to forbeare all further ſuites againſt <hi>Smith;</hi> Nor was there any further time ſpent vpon the ſaid hearing, then opening the ſaid Information, Suruey, and Certificate vpon the ſaid Commiſſion ſo awarded vpon the ſaid Information; which Decree was in effect as followeth, And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Crokey</hi> hath particularly Anſwered, which he (for your better information in all humility as becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth) doth preſent to the conſideration of your Maieſtie and this Honourable aſſembly.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="decree_and_answers">
                           <q>1. That whereas the cauſe by his Maieſtie was referred to the Lord <hi>Hobart,</hi> and the other two Iudges of the Common Pleas, touching the re-eſtabliſhing of the Schoole and poſſeſſions thereof according to the firſt foundation, and to ſettle a final end betweene <hi>Smith</hi> and <hi>Crokey</hi> for Warrens Court betweene them controuerted.</q>
                           <p>1. This is anſwered by the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion awarded by order in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and Certificate, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree thereupon, and vpon the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and arguing all exceptions, <hi>Sect. 27.</hi> And by the Rules made by <hi>Smithes</hi> aſſent, and concluding of Errors by like aſſent, <hi>Sect. 16.</hi> And by the Verdict and Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereupon with <hi>Smithes</hi> commitment for not yeelding poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsion to <hi>Crokey</hi> according to the Rules, <hi>Sect. 32.</hi> and according to <hi>Crokeys</hi> right affirmed by Verdicts, Nonſuites, Decrees and Orders in <hi>33.</hi> ſeuerall ſuites be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, <hi>Sect. 14. 36, 37.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <q>
                              <pb facs="tcp:14912:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>2. And whereas 14, Iuly 18. <hi>Regni regis Iacobi,</hi> the Lord <hi>Hobart</hi> &amp; other Iudges, did after ſeuerall hearings direct, that an Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation ſhould bee exhibited in the Court of Chancery againſt <hi>Smith</hi> and <hi>Crokey</hi> for the ſaid cauſes.</q>
                           <p>2. It ſeemeth to <hi>Crokey,</hi> that this Direction is derogatory, as to the words of that Reference, which was for auoyding of further ſuites, and not warranting any or other, then were then depending.</p>
                           <q>3. And that in Michaelmaſſe Terme following, an Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was exhibited, whereunto <hi>Smith</hi> and <hi>Crokey</hi> did in the ſame Terme Anſwer, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon an Order was made the 23. of Nouember in the ſame Terme whereby a Commiſſion was to bee awarded to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners to bee named by the Lord <hi>Hobart</hi> for ſurueying of the Schoole-lands, and of the Lands controuerted betweene <hi>Crokey</hi> and <hi>Smith.</hi> And becauſe <hi>Crokey</hi> attended not but betook himſelfe to other courſes, did not nominate the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. But the Lord Keeper i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>. <hi>Iulij</hi> 20. <hi>Regni regis Iacobi,</hi> did confirme the former Order of the 23. of Nouember: And that his Lordſhip did in open Court nominate the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners, and on the 19. of the ſame Iuly, his Maieſties Attourney did giue ſpeciall directions for execution of the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.</q>
                           <p>
                              <hi>3.</hi> An Information was ſo exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and orders ſo made, howbeit <hi>Crokey</hi> had good reaſon to goe on in that courſe vpon the Statute of Charitable vſes wherein he had begun, rather then to aſſent to any other, much leſſe to any thing that might haue withdrawne him from that courſe, and whereof his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, the Parliament, the Lord Archbiſhop, the Lord Chancellour, and others reuerend Biſhops were poſſeſſed, and had taken notice, and wherein the Parliament had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen order; wherupon a Commiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was awarded, and executed du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: And vpon that an Inquiſition, Certificate, and Decree were made and returned, which was a yeare before the ſaid Order of the <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>.</hi> of Iuly, and the order of the <hi>23.</hi> of Nouember was <hi>16.</hi> moneths before that of the <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>.</hi> of Iuly, ſo as <hi>Smith</hi> ſtirred not vpon that Information during the Parliament, but it no ſooner was ended, but <hi>Smith</hi> then began again to reuiue and ſet on foote all his former practices, all which, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                                 <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                              </gap> 
                              <hi>Crokey</hi> had rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to Withſtand.</p>
                           <q>
                              <pb facs="tcp:14912:24"/>4. That accordingly the ſaid Commiſſion was ſued forth, and in September following it was executed with great care and exactneſſe and a Suruey made, which in Michaelmaſſe Terme following was retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners Certificate, declaring that they did appoint o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſufficient men to Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey the premiſes with the Metts and bounds, appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them to attend with their Suruey at Wooton on the 10. of the ſame September: At which time they appointed for the Suruey (being approued of by <hi>Smith</hi> and <hi>Crokey</hi>) did deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in the Suruey, which was read in the preſence of <hi>Smith</hi> and <hi>Crokey,</hi> and of the Maior of Wooton and diuers others of the chiefe Townſmen there, &amp; of many others ſent for at the inſtance of <hi>Crokey,</hi> &amp; examined as witneſſes vpon their oathes, vpon Interrogatories by him exhibited, which vpon their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ions did agree with the Counterparts of Leaſes of the ſaid poſſeſſions voluntarily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by <hi>Smith,</hi> and that they found the Suruey to bee iuſt againſt which, neither of the defendants or others their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb facs="tcp:14912:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> did or could take any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions.</q>
                           <pb facs="tcp:14912:24"/>
                           <p>
                              <hi>4. Crokey</hi> did neither approue of that Suruey, nor Certificate an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed, nor did the Commiſsioners particularly examin Witneſſes vpon the Interrogatories, then preferred by <hi>Crokey</hi> as the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſsion requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, though <hi>Crokey</hi> much preſſed them thereto nor otherwiſe, then when as the Surveyors had brought in their ſurely, the ſame was read ouer, and then the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioners asked them then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent (which were onely ſuch as <hi>Smith</hi> would haue there) whether they could ſay any thing to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, without any further or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther examination, whereat <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>key</hi> ſhewed himſelfe much diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, and tooke exceptions at the then proceedings, and the ſame altogether diſliked and ſo told the Commiſsioners and ſome there aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled, nor was there any depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions or examinations vpon oath, nor bee any returned or vpon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord in that cauſe, nor did <hi>Smith</hi> then produce all the Courterparts of the Leaſes of the Schoole lands, but onely of ſuch parcels as hee pleaſed, and would not ſuffer any Tenant of the Schoole to produce any other, nor did <hi>Crokey</hi> allow of the Surveyors, for they had made the Suruey before <hi>Crokey</hi> did know of any ſuch matter, and they were <hi>Smithes</hi> neere neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours
<pb facs="tcp:14912:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> and friends, and ſuch as had ſome dependency on <hi>Smith:</hi> nor did there appeare aboue <hi>6.</hi> or <hi>7.</hi> of <hi>39.</hi> Tenants that <hi>Crokey</hi> would haue had there, and for which purpoſe he tendred their names to the Commiſsioners in writing, but they would not receiue it, nor ſend for more then for ſuch as <hi>Smith</hi> would haue. And in this manner was that Commiſsion executed.</p>
                           <q>5. That the ſubſtance of which Suruey declared in effect that the poſſeſſions of the Schoole did conſiſt of 31. houſes and 162. Acres and 10. pertches, And that the yearely Rent of the premiſes then was 21. pounds 4. ſhillings 6. pence. and that the yearely value of the premiſes to be improued aboue the ſaid Rents, was 121. pounds 17. ſhillings 2. pence, And that <hi>Warrens</hi> Court contained one Meſſuage, one fulling Mill, and 54. Acres, and 10. pertches, and that the yearely value of the ſame then was 38. pounds 1. ſhilling 4. pence, beſides 48. ſhillings and 12. ſhillings paya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble out of the ſame, And that of a Leaſe formerly made thereof, there was then vnexpired 10. yeares at Lady day next en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing.</q>
                           <p>
                              <hi>5. Smithes</hi> Patent from his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty doth mention <hi>39.</hi> Tenements as in truth there be, &amp; the land belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to Warrens Court by <hi>Smiths</hi> owne ſhewing amounteth to <hi>130.</hi> acres, as in the Section, &amp; the whole value of the Schoole lands is certified by the Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> the Biſhops <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> &amp; <hi>Winton,</hi> to be <hi>300.</hi> pound <hi>per annum</hi> or thereabouts, <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>key</hi> had <hi>21.</hi> yeares in <hi>Warrens</hi> Court, when hee firſt began ſuite againſt <hi>Smith,</hi> But further as to the preſent Reuenew of the Schoole <hi>Crokey</hi> doth affirme that it is at this day <hi>(re vera)</hi> worth about <hi>300.</hi> pound <hi>per annum</hi> and all in the diſpoſition of <hi>Smith,</hi> 
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> as for Leaſes in being there be none, but onely the remainder of the old Leaſe of <hi>88.</hi> yeares in <hi>Warrens</hi> Court belonging of right to <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>key,</hi> and ſuch Leaſes as <hi>Smith</hi> hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> made. As for the
<pb facs="tcp:14912:25"/> Leaſe of <hi>99.</hi> yeares ſuppoſed to be bought by <hi>Smith</hi> of the <hi>Duports,</hi> that Leaſe is fraudulent and ſo alwayes hath beene found.</p>
                           <q>
                              <pb facs="tcp:14912:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>6. That vpon the Information, Anſweres, Commiſſion, Certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficate, and Suruey, and by an Order made by his Lordſhip 12. December, in the ſaid 20. yeare of his late Maieſties reign for vſing of depoſitions former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken betweene <hi>Smith</hi> and <hi>Crokey</hi> in Chancery, the cauſe was heard, and at large debated by his Maieſties Attourney Generall in behalfe of the Schoole, Sergeant <hi>Crew,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Walter,</hi> Maſter <hi>Finch</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corder, and 6. others for <hi>Smith,</hi> and Sergeant <hi>Richardſon,</hi> Sir <hi>Laurence. Hide,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> for <hi>Crokey.</hi> And vpon the opening of the Information, Anſwers, reading of the Certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficate and Suruey, and vpon the long debating and deliberate hearing of the cauſe and all the circumſtances thereof, the truth of the cauſe appeared to be.</q>
                           <p>
                              <hi>6.</hi> This order as alſo the order there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in mentioned of the <hi>17.</hi> of Iuly. and the Certificate in that order of the <hi>17.</hi> of Iuly mentioned, were made (as it ſeemeth to <hi>Crokey</hi>) to no other intent but to bring in <hi>Crokey,</hi> and to make him liable to that ſuite brought into Chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vpon the ſaid Information for <hi>Crokeys</hi> owne particular cauſe touching <hi>Warrens</hi> Court. At which time <hi>Smith</hi> was impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for not yeelding to <hi>Crokey</hi> poſſeſsion according to the ſaid Rules in Court, But there was then no debating or deliberate hearing of the cauſe, nor was the cauſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe heard then the opening of the Information, Anſweres and reading of the Certificate and Suruey according to the Commiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on awarded vpon the Informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, howſoeuer the words of the Decree doe make ſhew of.</p>
                           <q>7. That in 8. <hi>Ricardi</hi> 2. <hi>Katherine</hi> Lady <hi>Berkley</hi> Widdow did ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the ſaid King and of <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Berkley</hi> then Lord of the fee Licence for founding the Schoole, to conſiſt of a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and two poore Schollers Collegiatly to liue together,
<pb facs="tcp:14912:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> and to haue a perpetuall ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, And for indowing the Schoole with the ſaid Lands 2. Feoffees were truſted by the Lady for purchaſing the ſaid Lands, to hold according to certaine ordinances by them to be made, and that accordingly the Schoole was founded, and the Lands aſſured by the Feof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fees to the Maſter and Schollers and their Succeſſors for euer; to be holden according to the ſaid Ordinances: And that the Schoole and poſſeſſions thereof were imployed according to the ſaid foundation and inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, vntill the 37. yeare of K. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.</q>
                           <p>
                              <hi>7. Crokey</hi> with this doth agree in all, ſauing that there were no or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances made but long before the foundation, To which Ordinances the foundation hath no relation, nor were there any Ordinances to bee made by the foundation, ſauing the Habendum therein, which
<pb facs="tcp:14912:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> onely declared the eſtate, as by the Certificate and Decree vpon the Commiſsion for charitable vſes expreſſed, and before related in the <hi>37.</hi> Section, Nor was the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation or inſtitution diſcontinued vntill <hi>Smith</hi> began his practices to ſupplant the Schoole. And <hi>Cold well</hi> was lawfully preſented and made Maſter of the Schoole, and the Leaſe by him granted of <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens</hi> Court was good in law: there hauing beene <hi>33.</hi> ſeuerall Suites in Affirmation of the ſame.</p>
                           <q>8 That on the 18. of May in the ſaid 37. yeare, <hi>Robert Coldwell</hi> then Schoolemaſter of the ſaid Schoole did demiſe Warrens Court vnto <hi>William Thomas</hi> his Executors and Aſſignes from Lady day then laſt paſt for 88. yeares for the yearely Rent of 48. ſhillings, and to the chiefe Lord 12. ſhillings <hi>per annum.</hi> And that the ſaid Leaſe was by the laſt will of <hi>William Thomas, annum</hi> 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4. <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                                    <desc>••••</desc>
                                 </gap> &amp; Maria</hi> bequeathed to <hi>Alice</hi> his wife for her life, and after her deceaſe to his Daughter <hi>Grace</hi> for her life, and after to remaine to <hi>Richard,
<pb facs="tcp:14912:26"/> William, Katherine, Ioice, Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> children of the ſaid <hi>Alice</hi> by one <hi>Iohn Moore</hi> her former husband, and made <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice</hi> his Executrix and dyed.</q>
                           <p>
                              <hi>8</hi> Crokey <hi>confeſſeth all this to bee true.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <q>9 That afterwards <hi>Alice</hi> intermar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with one <hi>Reignold Aphowell,</hi> and that <hi>Reignold</hi> and <hi>Alice anno</hi> 5. <hi>Elilizab.</hi> did demiſe the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes to the ſaid <hi>Richard Moore</hi> for 21. yeares, and that after in the 13. yeare of <hi>Q. Elizab. Reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nold</hi> did grant the remainder and Rent, and all his eſtate in <hi>Warrens</hi> Court to <hi>Iohn Sprint</hi> then husband of <hi>Ioyce.</hi> And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards in the ſaid 13. yeare of <hi>Q. Elizab.</hi> dyed, that <hi>Iohn Sprint</hi> in the ſame yeare did grant all his tytle to <hi>Alice,</hi> and that <hi>Alice anno</hi> 21. <hi>Eliz.</hi> did grant all her eſtate to <hi>Grace,</hi> and <hi>Grace</hi> being poſſeſſed <hi>anno</hi> 39. <hi>Eliz.</hi> did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termarry with <hi>Smith</hi> and dyed; And in this manner <hi>Smith</hi> made his tytle to <hi>Warrens</hi> Court, and affirmed that hee had diuers Verdicts and Nonſuites at the Common Law, and one De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, and three Diſmiſſions in Chancery for confirmation of his ſaid tytle.</q>
                           <pb facs="tcp:14912:26"/>
                           <p>
                              <hi>9.</hi> Whileſt <hi>Grace, Smiths</hi> firſt wife liued, <hi>Smith</hi> claimed no further or longer intereſt in <hi>Warrens</hi> Court then for her life. And as for <hi>Sprints</hi> tytle, it is but a meere ſuggeſtion and foyſted into this Decree, which <hi>Smith</hi> could neuer proue: Nor did <hi>Smith</hi> in this ſuite vpon the Information (being a part of the ground of this Decree) once endeuour or offer to proue any ſuch tytle. Nor did <hi>Smith</hi> ever ſpeake of that tytle of <hi>Sprints,</hi> vntill all the reſt of his tytles for the inheritance of all the Schoole lands fayled him, vpon which his tytles of inheritance to all, he ſtood ſo long as poſsibly hee might, and vntill he perceiued all his practices for maintenance thereof, were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered by <hi>Crokey,</hi> as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by that before related, <hi>Sect. 17.</hi> And by the Certificate and Decree vpon the Commiſsion for charitable vſes, <hi>Sect. 37. numero 1. 2.</hi> Beſides it appeareth by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall Anſweres of <hi>Alice</hi> and <hi>Grace</hi> in Chancery, <hi>Anno 26. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz.</hi> to the Bill of all the other Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees, that they made no further or other claime then for their ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall liues formerly related, <hi>Sect. 6. 7. &amp; 8.</hi> Nor hath there euer any Verdict, Nonſuite, Decree, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion paſſed in affirmation of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tytle controuerted betweene <hi>Smith</hi> &amp; <hi>Crokey.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <q>
                              <pb facs="tcp:14912:26"/>10. That <hi>Crokey</hi> made his tytle to Warrens Court by a Deede from <hi>Ioice</hi> (being Suruiuour of the 6. Legatees) by a Deed da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>anno</hi> 11. <hi>Regni regis Iacobi,</hi> and did affirme that hee had a Verdict for his tytle.</q>
                           <pb facs="tcp:14912:26"/>
                           <p>
                              <hi>10. Crokey</hi> doth affirme this to bee the true and only tytle, for which he hath had a final Tryall, Verdict, and Iudgement vpon a deliberate hearing, as is at large before rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>Sect. 16.</hi> and <hi>32.</hi> for which <hi>Smith</hi> hath beene twice commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Fleet for not yeelding poſſeſsion to <hi>Crokey.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <q>11. That it did appeare to the Court that <hi>anno</hi> 34. <hi>Eliz. Iohn Duport</hi> being Schoolemaſter, did demiſe <hi>Warrens</hi> Court and other the Schoole lands (except one Chamber and the Schoole-houſe) vnto his brother <hi>Iames Duport</hi> for 99. yeares for 40. ſhillings <hi>per annum;</hi> And that <hi>Iames Duport, anno</hi> 2. <hi>Iacobi</hi> for 100. pound fine, did make a Leaſe to <hi>Smith</hi> of <hi>Warrens</hi> Court for the reſidue of 99. years 10. dayes onely excepted, and in 6. <hi>Iacobi, Iames Duport</hi> did for 300. pound grant vnto <hi>Smith</hi> his whole eſtate in all the premiſes.</q>
                           <p>
                              <hi>11.</hi> If the Schoole and Poſſeſsions thereof, were neuer ſince <hi>37. H. 8.</hi> imployed according to the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation and inſtitution, then had <hi>Smith</hi> no reaſon to deale with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tytle from the <hi>Duports,</hi> much leſſe now to vrge any ſuch, But in that <hi>Smith</hi> bought in the <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports</hi> tytles, hee muſt needs ſhew his great deſire to ſupplant the Schoole, and to get the poſſeſsions thereof, and thereby to ecclips all other iuſt tytles. And <hi>Smith</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Lawyer) did alwayes well know that the <hi>Duports</hi> had no tytle to any part of the Schoole lands, nor lawfully placed in the Schoole, Nor did <hi>Smith</hi> euer giue <hi>100.</hi> pound for all his tytles. As for the <hi>40.</hi> ſhillings Rent ſuppoſed by <hi>Smith,</hi> that was a rent onely agreed vpon by <hi>Iohn</hi> and <hi>Iames Duport,</hi> whereas the ancient Rent of the Schoole was <hi>23. pound</hi> per annum, which <hi>Iames Duport</hi> deputy Schoolemaſter to <hi>Iohn Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port,</hi> did receiue vntill <hi>Smith</hi>
                              <pb facs="tcp:14912:27"/> had bought in manner as aforeſaid the <hi>Duports</hi> out.</p>
                           <q>
                              <pb facs="tcp:14912:27"/>12. That it did further appeare, that an Inquiſition was found <hi>anno</hi> 30. <hi>Elizab.</hi> That all the ſaid Lands were come to the Queen by the Statute of Chantryes made 1. <hi>Edward</hi> 6. And that the ſaid Q. 21. <hi>Marcij anno</hi> 31. did grant all the premiſes to <hi>Charles Badgehot</hi> and <hi>Bartholomew Yard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> and their heires vnder the yearely rent of xj. ſhillings. And that from them it came to <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew Phillips, Thomas Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine,</hi> and <hi>Edward Biſhop</hi> and their heires. And in the 15. yeare of his late Maieſties raign, <hi>Smith</hi> hauing beene in poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Warrens</hi> Court euer ſince his ſaid Mariage, did for 200. pound buy in the ſeuerall tytles and pretended eſtates. And for ſtrengthening his tytle, did for 5. pound obtaine another Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent vpon the Commiſſion of defectiue Tytles for xj. ſhillings rent.</q>
                           <p>
                              <hi>12. Smith</hi> practiced vpon theſe ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, as before vpon the <hi>Duports</hi> tytles, wel knowing all to be naught as may well appeare by the ſuite brought in the Exchequer between him and <hi>Biſhop, Sect. 17.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <q>13. That it did alſo appeare to the Court, that <hi>Smith</hi> did take a courſe for eſtabliſhing the Schoole (as formerly for 9. yeares before he had increaſed the Rent of 40. ſhillings to 12. pound <hi>per annu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                              </hi> to the Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter) And that whereas at that time by reaſon of the long Leaſe for 99. years the reuenew
<pb facs="tcp:14912:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> of the Schoole was but fortie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> 
                              <hi>per annum, Smith</hi> did conuey all the Premiſes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged of the long Leaſe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept that which lyeth in <hi>Nibley</hi> together with the fourth part of fines vpon Leaſes, and all the reſidue to other charitable purpoſes to certaine Feoffees and their heires to the vſe of the Schoolemaſter and his Succeſſors; And that <hi>Smith</hi> both in his Anſwer, and then in Court ſubmitted his tytles to the diſpoſing of the Court.</q>
                           <p>
                              <hi>13.</hi> That when <hi>Smithes</hi> backe was at wall, and that hee knew not what way to turne him by the oppoſition of <hi>Crokey.</hi> Then <hi>Smith</hi>) to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and face out the matter as he euer before did) might make ſuch a ſhew to the world when he meant nothing leſſe, for if hee had meant truly to the Schoole, and intended to haue maintained her firſt foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, he would neuer haue ſo practiced to haue ſupplantad it as before is ſhewed. And well hee might ſubmit all his tytles to the diſpoſition of the Chancery (none of them being good but all fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and he hauing no right at all)
<pb facs="tcp:14912:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> there conſiſting his onely hope when all others had failed him. Nor hath <hi>Smith</hi> laid open or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted all his tytles to the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery, for that tytle from <hi>Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Browning,</hi> and <hi>Bolton, Smith</hi> hath concealed and ſtill doth conceale the ſame, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent no doubt, but the ſame to reuiue and ſtand vpon in time to come, for the inheritance of all the Schoole lands when all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters now in hand ſhall bee dead and forgotten. As for the <hi>40.</hi> ſhillings &amp; <hi>12.</hi> pound Rent, the ſame is anſwered before, <hi>Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <q>14. And although <hi>Crokey</hi> for his owne ends had proſecuted ſome Commiſſions vpon the Statute of charitable vſes, yet it appeared by Affedauit Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and his owne Anſwere, that in the 16. of his Maieſties raigne he did giue in euidence at <hi>Wickwar</hi> to the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for concealed Lands, and that vpon his oath &amp; euidence by him produced, all the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes were found to be concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and that he tooke a Bond of 2000. pound of the proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the ſaid Commiſſion. That the Fee farme of <hi>Warrens</hi> Court ſhould be conueyed to him and his heires at the yeare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:14912:28"/> Rent of 40. ſhillings.</q>
                           <p>
                              <hi>14. Crokey</hi> did not ſo proſecute for his owne ends, but in behalfe of the Schoole onely, for <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>key</hi> did well know his tytle to <hi>Warrens</hi> Court to be good for the Statute of <hi>1. Edw: 6.</hi> maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth all Leaſes of Chantryes made before the <hi>28.</hi> day of Nouemb <hi>37. Hen. 8.</hi> as was the ſaid Leaſe vnder which <hi>Crokey</hi> claymes. For the Aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>dauit ſuppoſed to be made, <hi>Crokey</hi> cannot beleeue there was any ſuch, and if any ſuch matter were, then whether the ſame ſhould be ſo materiall, as whereupon to decree any point is the queſtion, But <hi>Crokey</hi> too well doth know that <hi>Smith</hi> was neuer without Affedauit Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.
<pb facs="tcp:14912:28"/> And for the Orders <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>key</hi> hath before anſwered in the <hi>26. Sect.</hi> Nor doth any ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter appeare by <hi>Crokeys</hi> Anſwer as is here foyſted into the Decree for <hi>Crokey</hi> by his Anſwer clee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himſelfe. And for the eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſuppoſed to bee giuen in by <hi>Crokey,</hi> that is cleered, <hi>Sect. 22. &amp; 23.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <q>15. That vpon conſideration of all which the Lord Keeper and Court of Chancery aſſiſted by Iuſtice <hi>Chamberlaine</hi> and Iuſtice <hi>Iones</hi> were of opinion, that the ſaid Lands did not come to the Crowne by the Statute of Chantryes, And that the ſaid long Leaſes are voide in Law and equitie, for either the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and Schollers are a Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giat Corporation, and then muſt ioyne in the Leaſes, which they did not, or elſe the ſaid Maſter was preſentatiue, and in that regard the ſaid Leaſes being made onely by the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and not confirmed by the Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> by whom by the foundation he was to be admitted, inſtituted, and ſworn to performe the ſaid Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are voide alſo. And for that the long Leaſes tend to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the Schoole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the intention of the Founder.</q>
                           <p>
                              <hi>15.</hi> It is not likely or probable, that it was the meaning of the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, that the <hi>2.</hi> Schollers ſhould be ioyned with the Maſter in let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Leaſes, for that there is no ſuch matter in the Inſtitutions or Ordinances, but thereby the two Schollers were to bee admitted at <hi>10.</hi> yeares at leaſt, and to continue there but <hi>6.</hi> yeares, and they were by the Ordinance ſubiect to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection by the Maſter. But it is plaine, that the Schoole lands were alwayes letten by the Schoolema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter onely; and for the Biſhops confirmation of the Leaſes, it is as vnlikely, nor can it be proued that there was euer any ſuch thing, nor doth the foundation mention any ſuch matter; nor were there any Ordinances made vpon by or after the foundation, but long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, nor was the ſame euer in queſtion or any part of the land. And yet <hi>Crokeys</hi> Anceſtors held <hi>Warrens</hi> Court for <hi>70.</hi>
                              <pb facs="tcp:14912:28"/> yeares vnder <hi>Coldwells</hi> Leaſe: And therefore it plainely appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, that all the ſaid points in this part of the Decree are but onely meere ſuppoſitions and ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions by <hi>Smith</hi> to delude the Court.</p>
                           <q>
                              <pb facs="tcp:14912:28"/>16. Therefore it was decreed that all the ſaid tytles both vnder the ſaid Letters Patents and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the ſaid Leaſes, and all other Leaſes and eſtates made by any Maſter ſhould be voyde, And all Bonds and Couenants made for ſecuring the ſame ſhould bee deliuered vp and cancelled; And that the ſame ſhould be called in, and all the poſſeſſions re-eſtabliſhed in the Schoole, and all the lands men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the ſaid Certificate and Suruey were decreed to the Schoole. And that if any other lands ſhould bee diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the Schoole, the Court would take ſuch further order for eſtabliſhing thereof to the Schoole as ſhould be fit. And that all the premiſes ſhould bee ſurrendred to his Maieſtie, that the ſame might be regranted to be imployed for the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Schoole, and the Maſter and Schollers there, and for the maintenance of a greater number of Schollers,
<pb facs="tcp:14912:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> according to the increaſe of the Reuenues as occaſion ſhould be.</q>
                           <p>
                              <hi>16.</hi> This clauſe taketh away <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keys</hi> lawfull tytle, It maketh voide the finall Tryall, and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict and Iudgement duly obtained and the Rules of Court for poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsion by conſent, as in the <hi>16. ſect.</hi> It altereth the ancient foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, which appropriateth the Patronage of the Schoole to the heires Males of the ſaid <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> Lord <hi>Berkley</hi> and the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance of the Schoole lands to the Schoolemaſter of that Schoole lawfully preſented as the ſame contin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ed for about <hi>200.</hi> yeares, and to transferre the ſaid Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage and inheritance by colour of ſuch a Surrender <hi>Crokey</hi> doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth whether it be warrantable by the Statute of charitable vſes, and whether the foundation may bee altered but by acte of Parliament. And what a reach <hi>Smith</hi> hath in this point of the Decree for get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in all his Bonds and Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants which hee hath runne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to for maintenance of his vniuſt tytle to the Scho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>le lands euery one may diſcerne.</p>
                           <q>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>7. And becauſe it appeared by the Suruey that diuers Meſſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and parcells of Land, part of the premiſes are and long had beene in the poſſeſſion of diuers, whereof many are of meane ability hauing paid fines. And if they ſhould bee remoued from the ſame would impoueriſh them, It was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore decreed, that they ſhould haue reaſonable Leaſes (not exceeding three liues) made to them without fine for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed Rent of a third part of the yearely value thereof ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſaid Suruey, and the opinion of the ſaid Iudges Aſſiſtants, and Maſter Attour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney generall, to whom his Lordſhip referred the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of this Decree.</q>
                           <pb facs="tcp:14912:29"/>
                           <p>
                              <hi>17.</hi> The Fines that they haue paid haue beene paid to <hi>Smith,</hi> and therefore <hi>Smith</hi> ſhould make them good being taken wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and that to make new Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes other than according to the firſt foundation: <hi>Crokey</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a queſtion whether it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the meaning of the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. It is not likely that Maſter Attourney Generall had any hand in this Decree, as it is entred vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on record. But that it was done by <hi>Smith</hi> himſelfe and his Councell. And very likely it is that <hi>Smith</hi> hath vſed ſome ſlight in procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſame to be thus entred. And that herein hee hath abuſed the Court, the Iudges and Maſter Attourney not caring whom hee abuſeth to worke his owne ends.</p>
                           <q>And becauſe <hi>Smith</hi> was in quiet poſſeſſion of <hi>Warrens</hi> Court for diuers yeares after his mariage, And that by buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the long Leaſe of 99. yeares, and eſtates of the Patentees hee had been at 700. pound charge, and had beſtowed great char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in building, and that many parcells of the Schoole lands lye in ſeuerall places intermixt
<pb facs="tcp:14912:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> and incloſed with his owne Fee ſimple lands.</q>
                           <p>18. <hi>Smith</hi> had neuer any quiet or lawfull poſſeſsion longer then his wife <hi>Grace</hi> liued, who dyed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>12.</hi> yeares ſince, and then <hi>Crokey</hi> claimed and entred, and euer ſince hath ſued for that his right to <hi>Warrens</hi> Court: Nor hath <hi>Smith</hi> beene at aboue <hi>100.</hi> pound charge as <hi>Crokey</hi> is infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in buying all the ſaid bad tytles, what he hath beſtowed in
<pb facs="tcp:14912:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> building was but to outface the world, and the better to colour thoſe his bad tytles. Nor doe the lands lye intermixt, but thoſe lands that <hi>Smith</hi> pretendeth to lye ſo, or the moſt thereof are lands alſo belonging to <hi>Warrens</hi> Court (for <hi>Smith</hi> hath made no accompt how he came by any other lands there) and are the reſidue of the <hi>130.</hi> Acres which <hi>Smith</hi> himſelfe hath confeſſed as before is ſaid in the <hi>15. Sect.</hi> though in this buſineſſe hee hath cauſed the ſame to be found but at <hi>58.</hi> Acres and <hi>10.</hi> perches that Suruey being vpon <hi>Smiths</hi> owne ſetting out, and wherein <hi>Crokey</hi> had no hand nor thereof any knowledge vntill it was done.</p>
                           <q>19. And that it appeared his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention was not to diminiſh the Reuenues of the Schoole being by the ſaid long Leaſe brought ſo low as 40. ſhillings <hi>per annum,</hi> but to increaſe the ſame, It was therefore decreed that <hi>Smith</hi> ſhould haue an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate in <hi>Warrens</hi> Court and of the intermixt lands in <hi>Nibley</hi> made to him for ſuch three liues or for yeares determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vpon ſuch three liues as hee ſhould nominate without im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment of waſte for a like increaſed Rent of a third part. And the heires and Aſſignes of <hi>Smith</hi> from time to time for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vpon requeſt, ſhould haue an eſtate of the ſame renewed to them in manner and for the Rent aforeſaid.</q>
                           <p>
                              <hi>19.</hi> It plainly appeareth that <hi>Smiths</hi> intention was not onely to dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the Reuenue of the Schoole, but vtterly to ſupplant, for ſo it appeareth.</p>
                           <p n="1">
                              <hi>1.</hi> By buying the <hi>Duports</hi> tytles mentioned, <hi>Sect. 10.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="2">
                              <hi>2.</hi> By buying the tytles of <hi>Cowper, Browning,</hi> and <hi>Bolton,</hi> mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>ſect. 10.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="3">
                              <hi>3.</hi> By letting Leaſes of the Schoole lands as his owne, <hi>ſect. 11.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="4">
                              <hi>4.</hi> By keeping of Courts in his owne name as Lord and owner of all Schoole lands, <hi>ſect. 11.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="5">
                              <hi>5.</hi> By his fraudulent ſuite brought
<pb facs="tcp:14912:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> in the Exchequer, wherein hee claymed a Fee ſimple in all the Schoole lands, <hi>ſect. 17.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="6">
                              <hi>6.</hi> By buying of <hi>Biſhops</hi> tytle, and taking a Patent vpon the Commiſsion of defectiue tytles of all the Schoole lands, <hi>ſect. 17.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="7">
                              <hi>7.</hi> By his Information brought againſt <hi>Crokey</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Ioice</hi> in the Common-Plea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>, wherein he ſet forth a ſeizen in fee of <hi>Warrens</hi> Court, <hi>ſect. 15.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="8">
                              <hi>8.</hi> By his Bill or Information in Starre-chamber a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Crokey</hi> and others, wherein hee made like claime, <hi>ſect. 17.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="9">
                              <hi>9.</hi> By managing all thoſe tytles from time to time, and ſo conſequently his owne tytle for the inheritance of all the Schoole lands, <hi>ſect. 17.</hi> and Certificate and Decree vpon the Commiſsion for charitable vſes, <hi>ſect. 37.</hi> numbers <hi>1. 2. 4. 6. &amp; per ordinum 23.</hi> Non. <hi>ſect.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="10">
                              <hi>10.</hi> By his labouring to make the Schoole lands Chantry lands, <hi>ſect. 17. 21. 22.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p n="11">
                              <hi>11.</hi> By croſsing and withſtanding at ſeuerall times his late Maieſties directions, and the directions and proceedings in Parliament <hi>Anno 1621.</hi> and of the Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> the Lords Biſhops of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Winton,</hi> the Lord Chancellor and Lord Keeper, and all <hi>Crokeys</hi> indeuours in behalfe of the Schoole, and by multiplicitie of cauſeleſſe ſuites, and his many other practices and delayes, all which being before manifeſtly proued. By decreeing and ſuch an eſtate to <hi>Smith</hi> and his heires, is vtterly to take away <hi>Crokeys</hi> tytle already duely determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and adiudged by Law, for <hi>Crokey</hi> after <hi>12.</hi> yeares oppoſition by <hi>Smith</hi> and againſt the opinion of the Lord Keeper mentioned, <hi>ſect.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <q>
                              <pb facs="tcp:14912:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>20. And becauſe the ſaid Leaſes were thereby dammed, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Court did forbeare to determine the tytle betweene the Defendants otherwiſe then by Decreeing the ſaid Leaſes to be voide, And did further order that all ſuites and proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions touching the tytle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Defendants ſhould ceaſe and ſeuerall Iniunctions were awarded againſt the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendants accordingly.</q>
                           <pb facs="tcp:14912:30"/>
                           <p>
                              <hi>20.</hi> Here is no difference made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Crokeys</hi> iuſt tytle pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the lawfull Leaſe of <hi>88.</hi> yeares made by <hi>Coldwell</hi> and the vnlawfull Leaſe of <hi>99.</hi> yeares made by <hi>Duport 60.</hi> yeares after, and it had beene all one to <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>key</hi> if the Court had in plaine termes taken away his tytle as to damme the Leaſe vnder which he claymeth and by which he hath right, and to debarre him of all further ſuites for his reliefe; As for debarring <hi>Smith</hi> from ſuites againſt <hi>Crokey</hi> there was no cauſe, and therefore that is but a ſhadow laid on by <hi>Smith</hi> to make the Iniunctions ſeeme equall.</p>
                           <q>21. And whereas the Iudges and Maſter Attourney did certifie his Lordſhip that vpon euery Tenants improuement the third part will amount to the increaſe of 47. pound <hi>per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> out of which they thought fit to aſſigne 26. pound 13. ſhillings 4. pence <hi>per annum,</hi> to the Schoolemaſter and fiue pound a peece for 4. Schollers, and their ſtipends and number might increaſe as the Reuenue ſhould increaſe by expiration of eſtates. It was therfore decreed, that 26. pound 13. ſhillings 4. pence ſhould be allowed to the Schoolemaſter, But with this
<pb facs="tcp:14912:31"/> that the Lord Keeper did thinke fit, and ſo did decree that there ſhould be fiue Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, and the ſtipend ſhould be foure pound <hi>per annum</hi> a peece. And the ſtipend and number to increaſe as ſhould the Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new; Sauing alwayes to the Court power to direct and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle the Regulement and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of the Schoole.</q>
                           <pb facs="tcp:14912:30"/>
                           <p>
                              <hi>20.</hi> Here is no difference made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Crokeys</hi> iuſt tytle pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the lawfull Leaſe of <hi>88.</hi> yeares made by <hi>Coldwell</hi> and the vnlawfull Leaſe of <hi>99.</hi> yeares made by <hi>Duport 60.</hi> yeares after, and it had beene all one to <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>key</hi> if the Court had in plaine termes taken away his tytle as to damme the Leaſe vnder which he claymeth and by which he hath right, and to debarre him of all further ſuites for his reliefe; As for debarring <hi>Smith</hi> from ſuites againſt <hi>Crokey</hi> there was no cauſe, and therefore that is but a ſhadow laid on by <hi>Smith</hi> to make the Iniunctions ſeeme equall.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> May it pleaſe this High and Honourable Aſſembly to obſerue, that the ſaid laſt recited Decree is grounded vpon a Commiſſion of Suruay without examination of any Witneſſes vpon Oath as the Commiſſion required, neither are any depoſitions of Record in that cauſe nor the Suruayers ſworne.</p>
               <p>Which Commiſſion of Suruay and Decree, proceeded by vertue of <hi>Smiths</hi> cautelous Petition to his late Majeſtie and Reference.</p>
               <p>Whereupon the late Lord Keeper granted the ſayd Commiſſion of Suruay as aforeſaid, which is meerely repugnant to the directions of the Lords Grace of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and proceedings of the late Lord Chancellor and diuers other Reuerent Biſhops, and contrary to the directions of the moſt Honorable the higher Houſe of Parliament, and the proceedings thereupon by Reuerent Biſhops and others, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Statute of Charitable vſes, as by the inquiſition De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree and Certificate found for the ſayd Schoole appeareth.</p>
               <p>Whereby <hi>Crokey</hi> humbly prayeth this Honourable Aſſembly to take in conſideration.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14912:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>had little expectation of any good ſucceſſe by that ſuite in Starchamber, being ſo foyled by that Decree in the ground and maine of all his ſuites againſt <hi>Smith.</hi> And yet <hi>Smith</hi> (vpon <hi>Crokeys</hi> forbearance in that Starchamber cauſe) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured 52. pounds coſts to be taxed againſt <hi>Crokey,</hi> though <hi>Crokey</hi> proceeded no further then to Bill and Anſwer of 3. Defendants, with which 52 pounds Coſts <hi>Crokey</hi> is now al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo charged in the Kings Bench.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Matters thus ſtanding, and being in this conflict betweene <hi>Crokey</hi> and <hi>Smith.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>May it pleaſe your Maieſtie, and the reſt of this high and Honourable aſſembly to conſider by how many waies, all in places Iudicature and authority may be deluded, and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the adminiſtration of Iuſtice, by Impoſtors, practices, plotters, and deceiuers, that bend their mindes and indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours wholly to iniurie and oppreſſion, without regard whom they delude, deceiue, and abuſe, for their owne im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious ends, ſeeming not to dread any puniſhment either in this life, or in the life to come, moſt impiouſly outfacing and deluding all Iuſtice and authority, as in this man <hi>Smith,</hi> your Maieſtie and the reſt by this plaine Relation may diſcerne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Crokeys</hi> moſt humble ſuite wherefore, is in the concluſion as in the beginning: And that the matters before ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, and wherewith <hi>Smith</hi> is charged, may be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by this high and Honourable Aſſembly that the right may appeare, and ſo be adiudged and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, and in ſuch ſort as ſhall ſeeme moſt fit, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Crokey</hi> vnder reformation particularly offereth to conſideration the particulars inſuing, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the Commiſſion, Inquiſition, Certificate, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, vpon the Statute of charitable vſes by direction of Parliament 16. may be maintained and proſecuted; and that the ſaid laſt recited Decree in Chancery to euery point whereof <hi>Crokey</hi> hath anſwered, may bee made voyde by
<pb facs="tcp:14912:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> authoritie of this preſent Parliament.</p>
               <p>That the Schoole and poſſeſſions thereto belonging may be reduced according to the meaning of the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, with ſuch other additions as this high Court ſhall hold meet and agreeable to the time.</p>
               <p>That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Peter Bird,</hi> placed vpon part of the Schoole lands by <hi>Smithes</hi> meanes, and <hi>Cowper</hi> now pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced as Schoolemaſter may be remoued, for that they haue beene, and are practicers with <hi>Smith</hi> in all or moſt of his deſignes for ſupplanting the Schoole, and his inſtruments alwayes ready to execute any euill act for <hi>Smith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what order it ſhall pleaſe your Maieſtie and this high Court to award for <hi>Crokey,</hi> in reſpect of his long and great expence of his whole eſtate and more, to the value of 2200. pounds for the rectifying of the ſaid Schoole, and defending the tytle of the Schoole, to the vtter neglect of all his owne affaires, being before a Merchant of good cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit and trading.</p>
               <p>And for <hi>Crokeys</hi> right and poſſeſſion to and in <hi>Warrens</hi> Court according to his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ence, and according to the Finall triall, Verdict, Iudgement, and Rules in Court, and according to his Maieſties directions mentioned in Section the 30.</p>
               <p>And for the meane profits of <hi>Warrens</hi> Court worth 80. pound <hi>per annum,</hi> by <hi>Smith</hi> wrongfully kept from him ſince <hi>Crokeys</hi> firſt entry, which is 12. yeares.</p>
               <p>And for the 297. pounds Coſts which <hi>Smith</hi> was to pay <hi>Crokey</hi> for wrong vexation in Starchamber ſome 7. years detained, as by the Diſmiſſion and ſeuerall Orders, and Bill of Coſts mentioned, Section 18.</p>
               <p>For the remitting of the 52. pounds Coſts obtained by <hi>Smith</hi> vnduly in Starchamber againſt <hi>Crokey</hi> vpon Bill and Anſwer mentioned in the 41. Section, for <hi>Crokeyes</hi> great labour and toyle both of his body and minde
<pb facs="tcp:14912:32"/> 12. yeares together, with the waſting and conſuming of his vitall ſpirits in bearing the aſſaults and inſufferable wrongs of <hi>Smithes</hi> impietie, and improbiety in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of the ſaid Schoole being moued thereunto for Gods cauſe, and no benefit to himſelfe without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution of any, with the blame of many of his dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt friends for ſo great earneſtneſſe in a common cauſe generally neglected and violently oppoſed, that vnleſſe the ſpeciall mercy and great goodneſſe of God had aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted and ſtrengthened his weakeneſſe in ſo ſore a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict, in ſo iuſt a cauſe, which <hi>Crokey</hi> holdeth to be more pretious then life it ſelfe, (as in the 4. Chapter of <hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticus</hi> the 28. verſe) <hi>Striue for the truth vnto death, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend Iuſtice for thy life, and the Lord God ſhall fight for thee againſt thine enemies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Vnto all which <hi>Crokey</hi> moſt humbly ſubmits himſelfe.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
